<!-- <!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"> -->
<!-- $Id: installation.xml,v 1.136.2.7 2007/12/19 00:43:20 mkanat%bugzilla.org Exp $ -->
<chapter id="installing-bugzilla">
  <title>Installing Bugzilla</title>

  <section id="installation">
    <title>Installation</title>

    <note>
      <para>If you just want to <emphasis>use</emphasis> Bugzilla, 
      you do not need to install it. None of this chapter is relevant to
      you. Ask your Bugzilla administrator
      for the URL to access it over the web.
      </para>
    </note>

    <para>The Bugzilla server software is usually installed on Linux or 
    Solaris. 
    If you are installing on another OS, check <xref linkend="os-specific"/>
    before you start your installation to see if there are any special
    instructions.
    </para>

    <para>
      As an alternative to following these instructions, you may wish to
      try Arne Schirmacher's unofficial and unsupported 
      <ulink url="http://www.softwaretesting.de/article/view/33/1/8/">Bugzilla
      Installer</ulink>, which installs Bugzilla and all its prerequisites
      on Linux or Solaris systems.
    </para>

    <para>This guide assumes that you have administrative access to the
    Bugzilla machine. It not possible to
    install and run Bugzilla itself without administrative access except
    in the very unlikely event that every single prerequisite is
    already installed.
    </para>

    <warning>
      <para>The installation process may make your machine insecure for
      short periods of time. Make sure there is a firewall between you
      and the Internet.
      </para>
    </warning>

    <para>
    You are strongly recommended to make a backup of your system
    before installing Bugzilla (and at regular intervals thereafter :-).
    </para>

    <para>In outline, the installation proceeds as follows:
    </para>

    <procedure>
      <step>
        <para><link linkend="install-perl">Install Perl</link>
        (&min-perl-ver; or above for non-Windows platforms; &min-perl-ver-win;
        for Windows)
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para><link linkend="install-database">Install a Database Engine</link>
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para><link linkend="install-webserver">Install a Webserver</link>
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para><link linkend="install-bzfiles">Install Bugzilla</link>
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para><link linkend="install-perlmodules">Install Perl modules</link>
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          <link linkend="install-MTA">Install a Mail Transfer Agent</link>
          (Sendmail 8.7 or above, or an MTA that is Sendmail-compatible with at least this version)
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>Configure all of the above.
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>

    <section id="install-perl">
      <title>Perl</title>

      <para>Installed Version Test: <filename>perl -v</filename></para>
      
      <para>Any machine that doesn't have Perl on it is a sad machine indeed.
      If you don't have it and your OS doesn't provide official packages, 
      visit <ulink url="http://www.perl.com"/>.
      Although Bugzilla runs with Perl &min-perl-ver;,
      it's a good idea to be using the latest stable version.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="install-database">
      <title>Database Engine</title>
      
      <para>From Bugzilla 2.20, support is included for using both the MySQL and
      PostgreSQL database servers. You only require one of these systems to make
      use of Bugzilla.</para>

      <section id="install-mysql">
          <title>MySQL</title>
          <para>Installed Version Test: <filename>mysql -V</filename></para>
      
          <para>
          If you don't have it and your OS doesn't provide official packages, 
          visit <ulink url="http://www.mysql.com"/>. You need MySQL version
          &min-mysql-ver; or higher.
          </para>
      
          <note>
            <para> Many of the binary
            versions of MySQL store their data files in 
            <filename class="directory">/var</filename>.
            On some Unix systems, this is part of a smaller root partition,
            and may not have room for your bug database. To change the data
            directory, you have to build MySQL from source yourself, and
            set it as an option to <filename>configure</filename>.</para>
          </note> 
           
          <para>If you install from something other than a packaging/installation
          system, such as .rpm (Redhat Package), .deb (Debian Package), .exe
          (Windows Executable), or .msi (Microsoft Installer), make sure the MySQL
          server is started when the machine boots.
          </para>
      </section>
      
      <section id="install-pg">
          <title>PostgreSQL</title>
          <para>Installed Version Test: <filename>psql -V</filename></para>
      
          <para>
          If you don't have it and your OS doesn't provide official packages, 
          visit <ulink url="http://www.postgresql.org/"/>. You need PostgreSQL
          version &min-pg-ver; or higher.
          </para>
           
          <para>If you install from something other than a packaging/installation
          system, such as .rpm (Redhat Package), .deb (Debian Package), .exe
          (Windows Executable), or .msi (Microsoft Installer), make sure the
          PostgreSQL server is started when the machine boots.
          </para>
      </section>
      
    </section>
    
    <section id="install-webserver">
      <title>Web Server</title>

      <para>Installed Version Test: view the default welcome page at
      http://&lt;your-machine&gt;/</para>
      
      <para>You have freedom of choice here, pretty much any web server that
      is capable of running <glossterm linkend="gloss-cgi">CGI</glossterm>
      scripts will work.
       However, we strongly recommend using the Apache web server
       (either 1.3.x or 2.x), and 
       the installation instructions usually assume you are
        using it. If you have got Bugzilla working using another webserver,
        please share your experiences with us by filing a bug in &bzg-bugs;.
      </para>
      
      <para>
      If you don't have Apache and your OS doesn't provide official packages, 
      visit <ulink url="http://httpd.apache.org/"/>.
      </para>

    </section>

    <section id="install-bzfiles">
      <title>Bugzilla</title>

      <para>
        Download a Bugzilla tarball (or check it out from CVS) and place
        it in a suitable directory, accessible by the default web server user 
        (probably <quote>apache</quote> or <quote>www</quote>). 
        Good locations are either directly in the main web space for your
        web server or perhaps in 
        <filename>/usr/local</filename>
        with a symbolic link from the web space.
      </para>

      <caution>
        <para>The default Bugzilla distribution is NOT designed to be placed
        in a <filename class="directory">cgi-bin</filename> directory. This
        includes any directory which is configured using the
        <option>ScriptAlias</option> directive of Apache.
        </para>
      </caution>
      
      <para>Once all the files are in a web accessible directory, make that
      directory writable by your webserver's user. This is a temporary step
      until you run the 
      <filename>checksetup.pl</filename>
      script, which locks down your installation.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="install-perlmodules">
      <title>Perl Modules</title>
      
      <para>Bugzilla's installation process is based
      on a script called <filename>checksetup.pl</filename>. 
      The first thing it checks is whether you have appropriate 
      versions of all the required
      Perl modules. The aim of this section is to pass this check. 
      When it passes, proceed to <xref linkend="configuration"/>.
      </para>
      
      <para>
      At this point, you need to <filename>su</filename> to root. You should
      remain as root until the end of the install. To check you have the
      required modules, run:
      </para>
      
      <screen><prompt>bash#</prompt> ./checksetup.pl --check-modules</screen>
 
      <para>
        <filename>checksetup.pl</filename> will print out a list of the
        required and optional Perl modules, together with the versions
        (if any) installed on your machine.
        The list of required modules is reasonably long; however, you 
        may already have several of them installed.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        There is a meta-module called Bundle::Bugzilla, 
        which installs all the other 
        modules with a single command. You should use this if you are running
        Perl 5.6.1 or above.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        The preferred way of installing Perl modules is via CPAN on Unix, 
        or PPM on Windows (see <xref linkend="win32-perl-modules"/>). These
        instructions assume you are using CPAN; if for some reason you need 
        to install the Perl modules manually, see 
        <xref linkend="install-perlmodules-manual"/>.
      </para>  
        
      <screen><prompt>bash#</prompt> perl -MCPAN -e 'install "&lt;modulename&gt;"'</screen>

      <para>
        If you using Bundle::Bugzilla, invoke the magic CPAN command on it.
        Otherwise, you need to work down the 
        list of modules that <filename>checksetup.pl</filename> says are
        required, in the order given, invoking the command on each.
      </para>
      
      <tip>
        <para>Many people complain that Perl modules will not install for
        them. Most times, the error messages complain that they are missing a
        file in 
        <quote>@INC</quote>.
        Virtually every time, this error is due to permissions being set too
        restrictively for you to compile Perl modules or not having the
        necessary Perl development libraries installed on your system.
        Consult your local UNIX systems administrator for help solving these
        permissions issues; if you 
        <emphasis>are</emphasis>
        the local UNIX sysadmin, please consult the newsgroup/mailing list
        for further assistance or hire someone to help you out.</para>
      </tip>

      <note>
        <para>If you are using a package-based system, and attempting to install the
        Perl modules from CPAN, you may need to install the "development" packages for
        MySQL and GD before attempting to install the related Perl modules. The names of
        these packages will vary depending on the specific distribution you are using,
        but are often called <filename>&lt;packagename&gt;-devel</filename>.</para>
      </note>
 
      <para>
        Here is a complete list of modules and their minimum versions.
        Some modules have special installation notes, which follow.
      </para>

      <para>Required Perl modules:
      <orderedlist>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            CGI &min-cgi-ver; or CGI &min-mp-cgi-ver; if using mod_perl
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Date::Format (&min-date-format-ver;)
          </para>
        </listitem>
    
        <listitem>
          <para>
            DBI (&min-dbi-ver;)
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            <link linkend="install-modules-dbd-mysql">DBD::mysql</link>
            (&min-dbd-mysql-ver;) if using MySQL
          </para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para>
            DBD::Pg (&min-dbd-pg-ver;) if using PostgreSQL
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            File::Spec (&min-file-spec-ver;)
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            <link linkend="install-modules-template">Template</link>
            (&min-template-ver;)
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Email::Send (&min-email-send-ver;)
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Email::MIME::Modifier (&min-email-mime-modifier-ver;)
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      Optional Perl modules:
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <link linkend="install-modules-gd">GD</link>
            (&min-gd-ver;) for bug charting
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Template::Plugin::GD::Image
            (&min-gd-ver;) for Graphical Reports
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            <link linkend="install-modules-chart-base">Chart::Base</link>
            (&min-chart-base-ver;) for bug charting
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            <link linkend="install-modules-gd-graph">GD::Graph</link>
            (&min-gd-graph-ver;) for bug charting
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            <link linkend="install-modules-gd-text">GD::Text</link>
            (&min-gd-text-ver;) for bug charting
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            <link linkend="install-modules-xml-twig">XML::Twig</link>
            (&min-xml-twig-ver;) for bug import/export
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            MIME::Parser (&min-mime-parser-ver;) for bug import/export
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            LWP::UserAgent
            (&min-lwp-useragent-ver;) for Automatic Update Notifications
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            <link linkend="install-modules-patchreader">PatchReader</link>
            (&min-patchreader-ver;) for pretty HTML view of patches
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Image::Magick (&min-image-magick-ver;) for converting BMP image attachments to PNG
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Net::LDAP
            (&min-net-ldap-ver;) for LDAP Authentication
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            <link linkend="install-modules-soap-lite">SOAP::Lite</link>
            (&min-soap-lite-ver;) for the web service interface
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            HTML::Parser
            (&min-html-parser-ver;) for More HTML in Product/Group Descriptions
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            HTML::Scrubber
            (&min-html-scrubber-ver;) for More HTML in Product/Group Descriptions
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Email::MIME::Attachment::Stripper
            (&min-email-mime-attachment-stripper-ver;) for Inbound Email
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Email::Reply
            (&min-email-reply-ver;) for Inbound Email
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            mod_perl2
            (&min-mod_perl2-ver;) for mod_perl
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            CGI
            (&min-cgi-ver;) for mod_perl
          </para>
        </listitem>

      </orderedlist>
      </para>

      <section id="install-modules-dbd-mysql">
        <title>DBD::mysql</title>

        <para>The installation process will ask you a few questions about the
        desired compilation target and your MySQL installation. For most of the
        questions the provided default will be adequate, but when asked if your
        desired target is the MySQL or mSQL packages, you should
        select the MySQL-related ones. Later you will be asked if you wish to
        provide backwards compatibility with the older MySQL packages; you
        should answer YES to this question. The default is NO.</para>

        <para>A host of 'localhost' should be fine. A testing user of 'test',
        with a null password, should have sufficient access to run
        tests on the 'test' database which MySQL creates upon installation.
        </para>
      </section>

      <section id="install-modules-template">
        <title>Template Toolkit (&min-template-ver;)</title>

        <para>When you install Template Toolkit, you'll get asked various
        questions about features to enable. The defaults are fine, except
        that it is recommended you use the high speed XS Stash of the Template
        Toolkit, in order to achieve best performance.
        </para>
      </section> 

      <section id="install-modules-gd">
        <title>GD (&min-gd-ver;)</title>

        <para>The GD module is only required if you want graphical reports.
        </para>

        <note>
          <para>The Perl GD module requires some other libraries that may or
          may not be installed on your system, including 
          <classname>libpng</classname>
          and 
          <classname>libgd</classname>. 
          The full requirements are listed in the Perl GD module README.
          If compiling GD fails, it's probably because you're
          missing a required library.</para>
        </note>

        <tip>
          <para>The version of the GD module you need is very closely tied
          to the <classname>libgd</classname> version installed on your system.
          If you have a version 1.x of <classname>libgd</classname> the 2.x
          versions of the GD module won't work for you.
         </para>
       </tip>
      </section>

      <section id="install-modules-chart-base">
        <title>Chart::Base (&min-chart-base-ver;)</title>

        <para>The Chart::Base module is only required if you want graphical 
        reports. 
        Note that earlier versions that 0.99c used GIFs, which are no longer
        supported by the latest versions of GD.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="install-modules-gd-graph">
        <title>GD::Graph (&min-gd-graph-ver;)</title>

        <para>The GD::Graph module is only required if you want graphical 
        reports.
        </para>
      </section>

      <section id="install-modules-gd-text">
        <title>GD::Text (&min-gd-text-ver;)</title>

        <para>The GD::Text module is only required if you want graphical 
        reports.
        </para>
      </section>

      <section id="install-modules-xml-twig">
        <title>XML::Twig (&min-xml-twig-ver;)</title>

        <para>The XML::Twig module is only required if you want to import
        XML bugs using the <filename>importxml.pl</filename>
        script. This is required to use Bugzilla's "move bugs" feature;
        you may also want to use it for migrating from another bug database.
        </para>
      </section>

      <section id="install-modules-soap-lite">
        <title>SOAP::Lite (&min-soap-lite-ver;)</title>
        <para>Installing SOAP::Lite enables your Bugzilla installation to be
        accessible at a standardized Web Service interface (SOAP/XML-RPC)
        by third-party applications via HTTP(S).
        </para>
      </section>

      <section id="install-modules-patchreader">
        <title>PatchReader (&min-patchreader-ver;)</title>

        <para>The PatchReader module is only required if you want to use
        Patch Viewer, a
        Bugzilla feature to show code patches in your web browser in a more
        readable form.
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section id="install-MTA">
      <title>Mail Transfer Agent (MTA)</title>
    
      <para>
        Bugzilla is dependent on the availability of an e-mail system for its 
        user authentication and for other tasks.
      </para>

      <note>
        <para>
          This is not entirely true.  It is possible to completely disable 
          email sending, or to have Bugzilla store email messages in a 
          file instead of sending them.  However, this is mainly intended 
          for testing, as disabling or diverting email on a production 
          machine would mean that users could miss important events (such 
          as bug changes or the creation of new accounts).
        </para>

        <para>
          For more information, see the <quote>mail_delivery_method</quote> parameter
          in <xref linkend="parameters" />.
        </para>
      </note>
    
      <para>
        On Linux, any Sendmail-compatible MTA (Mail Transfer Agent) will 
        suffice.  Sendmail, Postfix, qmail and Exim are examples of common 
        MTAs. Sendmail is the original Unix MTA, but the others are easier to 
        configure, and therefore many people replace Sendmail with Postfix or 
        Exim. They are drop-in replacements, so Bugzilla will not 
        distinguish between them.
      </para>

      <para>
        If you are using Sendmail, version 8.7 or higher is required.
        If you are using a Sendmail-compatible MTA, it must be congruent with 
        at least version 8.7 of Sendmail.
      </para>

      <para>
        Consult the manual for the specific MTA you choose for detailed 
        installation instructions. Each of these programs will have their own 
        configuration files where you must configure certain parameters to 
        ensure that the mail is delivered properly. They are implemented 
        as services, and you should ensure that the MTA is in the auto-start 
        list of services for the machine.
      </para>

      <para>
        If a simple mail sent with the command-line 'mail' program 
        succeeds, then Bugzilla should also be fine.
      </para>

    </section>  
    <section id="using-mod_perl-with-bugzilla">
      <title>Installing Bugzilla on mod_perl</title>
      <para>It is now possible to run the Bugzilla software under <literal>mod_perl</literal> on
      Apache. <literal>mod_perl</literal> has some additional requirements to that of running
      Bugzilla under <literal>mod_cgi</literal> (the standard and previous way).</para>
      
      <para>Bugzilla requires <literal>mod_perl</literal> to be installed, which can be
      obtained from <ulink url="http://perl.apache.org"/> - Bugzilla requires
      version &min-mod_perl2-ver; (AKA 2.0.0-RC5) to be installed.</para>
      
      <para>Bugzilla also requires a more up-to-date version of the CGI
      perl module to be installed, version &min-mp-cgi-ver; as opposed to &min-cgi-ver;
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  
  <section id="configuration">
    <title>Configuration</title>

    <warning>
      <para>
        Poorly-configured MySQL and Bugzilla installations have
        given attackers full access to systems in the past. Please take the
        security parts of these guidelines seriously, even for Bugzilla 
        machines hidden away behind your firewall. Be certain to read
        <xref linkend="security"/> for some important security tips.
      </para>      
    </warning>

    <section id="localconfig">
      <title>localconfig</title>
      
      <para>
        You should now run <filename>checksetup.pl</filename> again, this time
        without the <literal>--check-modules</literal> switch.
      </para>
      <screen><prompt>bash#</prompt> ./checksetup.pl</screen>
      <para>
        This time, <filename>checksetup.pl</filename> should tell you that all
        the correct modules are installed and will display a message about, and
        write out a  file called, <filename>localconfig</filename>. This file
        contains the default settings for a number of Bugzilla parameters.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        Load this file in your editor. The only value you 
        <emphasis>need</emphasis> to change is $db_pass, the password for
        the user you will create for your database. Pick a strong
        password (for simplicity, it should not contain single quote
        characters) and put it here.
      </para>

      <para>
        You may need to change the value of 
        <emphasis>webservergroup</emphasis> if your web server does not 
        run in the "apache" group.  On Debian, for example, Apache runs in 
        the "www-data" group.  If you are going to run Bugzilla on a 
        machine where you do not have root access (such as on a shared web 
        hosting account), you will need to leave
        <emphasis>webservergroup</emphasis> empty, ignoring the warnings 
        that <filename>checksetup.pl</filename> will subsequently display 
        every time it is run.
      </para>
      
      <caution>
        <para>
          If you are using suexec, you should use your own primary group
          for <emphasis>webservergroup</emphasis> rather than leaving it
          empty, and see the additional directions in the suexec section
          <xref linkend="suexec" />.
        </para>
      </caution>

      <para>
        The other options in the <filename>localconfig</filename> file
        are documented by their accompanying comments. If you have a slightly
        non-standard MySQL setup, you may wish to change one or more of
        the other "$db_*" parameters. 
      </para>
      
      <para>
        You may also wish to change the names of 
        the priorities, severities, operating systems and platforms for your
        installation. However, you can always change these after installation
        has finished; if you then re-run <filename>checksetup.pl</filename>,
        the changes will get picked up.
      </para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="database-engine">
      <title>Database Server</title>
      <para>
        This section deals with configuring your database server for use
        with Bugzilla. Currently, MySQL (<xref linkend="mysql"/>) and
        PostgreSQL (<xref linkend="postgresql"/>) are available.
      </para>

      <section id="database-schema">
        <title>Bugzilla Database Schema</title>

        <para>
          The Bugzilla database schema is available at
          <ulink url="http://www.ravenbrook.com/project/p4dti/tool/cgi/bugzilla-schema/">Ravenbrook</ulink>.
          This very valuable tool can generate a written description of
          the Bugzilla database schema for any version of Bugzilla. It
          can also generate a diff between two versions to help someone
          see what has changed.
        </para>
      </section>

      <section id="mysql">
        <title>MySQL</title>

        <caution>
          <para>
            MySQL's default configuration is very insecure.
            <xref linkend="security-mysql"/> has some good information for
            improving your installation's security.
          </para>
        </caution>
        
        <section id="install-setupdatabase">
          <title>Allow large attachments</title>
        
          <para>
            By default, MySQL will only accept packets up to 64Kb in size.
            If you want to have attachments larger than this, you will need
            to modify your <filename>/etc/my.cnf</filename> as below.
          </para>

          <screen>  [mysqld]
  # Allow packets up to 1M
  max_allowed_packet=1M</screen>

          <para>
            There is also a parameter in Bugzilla called 'maxattachmentsize'
            (default = 1000 Kb) that controls the maximum allowable attachment
            size. Attachments larger than <emphasis>either</emphasis> the 
            'max_allowed_packet' or 'maxattachmentsize' value will not be
            accepted by Bugzilla.
          </para>

          <note>
            <para>
              This does not affect Big Files, attachments that are stored directly
              on disk instead of in the database.  Their maximum size is
              controlled using the 'maxlocalattachment' parameter.
            </para>
          </note>
        </section>
        
        <section>
          <title>Allow small words in full-text indexes</title>

          <para>By default, words must be at least four characters in length
          in order to be indexed by MySQL's full-text indexes. This causes
          a lot of Bugzilla specific words to be missed, including "cc",
          "ftp" and "uri".</para>

          <para>MySQL can be configured to index those words by setting the
          ft_min_word_len param to the minimum size of the words to index.
          This can be done by modifying the <filename>/etc/my.cnf</filename>
          according to the example below:</para>

          <screen>  [mysqld]
  # Allow small words in full-text indexes
  ft_min_word_len=2</screen>

          <para>Rebuilding the indexes can be done based on documentation found at
          <ulink url="http://www.mysql.com/doc/en/Fulltext_Fine-tuning.html"/>.
          </para>
        </section>
        
        <section id="install-setupdatabase-adduser">
          <title>Add a user to MySQL</title>

          <para>
            You need to add a new MySQL user for Bugzilla to use.
            (It's not safe to have Bugzilla use the MySQL root account.)
            The following instructions assume the defaults in
            <filename>localconfig</filename>; if you changed those,
            you need to modify the SQL command appropriately. You will
            need the <replaceable>$db_pass</replaceable> password you
            set in <filename>localconfig</filename> in 
            <xref linkend="localconfig"/>.
          </para>

          <para>
            We use an SQL <command>GRANT</command> command to create
            a <quote>bugs</quote> user. This also restricts the 
            <quote>bugs</quote>user to operations within a database
            called <quote>bugs</quote>, and only allows the account
            to connect from <quote>localhost</quote>. Modify it to
            reflect your setup if you will be connecting from another
            machine or as a different user.
          </para>
        
          <para>
            Run the <filename>mysql</filename> command-line client and enter:
          </para>

          <screen>  <prompt>mysql&gt;</prompt> GRANT SELECT, INSERT,
           UPDATE, DELETE, INDEX, ALTER, CREATE, LOCK TABLES,
           CREATE TEMPORARY TABLES, DROP, REFERENCES ON bugs.*
           TO bugs@localhost IDENTIFIED BY '<replaceable>$db_pass</replaceable>';
           <prompt>mysql&gt;</prompt> FLUSH PRIVILEGES;</screen>

        </section>      
        
        <section>
          <title>Permit attachments table to grow beyond 4GB</title>

          <para>
            By default, MySQL will limit the size of a table to 4GB.
            This limit is present even if the underlying filesystem
            has no such limit.  To set a higher limit, follow these
            instructions.
          </para>

          <para>
            After you have completed the rest of the installation (or at least the
            database setup parts), you should run the <filename>MySQL</filename>
            command-line client and enter the following, replacing <literal>$bugs_db</literal>
            with your Bugzilla database name (<emphasis>bugs</emphasis> by default):
          </para>

          <screen>
            <prompt>mysql&gt;</prompt> use <replaceable>$bugs_db</replaceable>
            <prompt>mysql&gt;</prompt> ALTER TABLE attachments 
            AVG_ROW_LENGTH=1000000, MAX_ROWS=20000;
          </screen>

          <para>
            The above command will change the limit to 20GB. Mysql will have 
            to make a temporary copy of your entire table to do this. Ideally, 
            you should do this when your attachments table is still small. 
          </para>

          <note>
            <para>
              This does not affect Big Files, attachments that are stored directly
              on disk instead of in the database.
            </para>
          </note>
        </section>
      </section>
      
      <section id="postgresql">
        <title>PostgreSQL</title>
        <section>
          <title>Add a User to PostgreSQL</title>

          <para>You need to add a new user to PostgreSQL for the Bugzilla
          application to use when accessing the database. The following instructions
          assume the defaults in <filename>localconfig</filename>; if you
          changed those, you need to modify the commands appropriately. You will
          need the <replaceable>$db_pass</replaceable> password you
          set in <filename>localconfig</filename> in 
          <xref linkend="localconfig"/>.</para>

          <para>On most systems, to create the user in PostgreSQL, you will need to
          login as the root user, and then</para>

          <screen> <prompt>bash#</prompt> su - postgres</screen>

          <para>As the postgres user, you then need to create a new user: </para>
            
          <screen> <prompt>bash$</prompt> createuser -U postgres -dAP bugs</screen>
 
          <para>When asked for a password, provide the password which will be set as
          <replaceable>$db_pass</replaceable> in <filename>localconfig</filename>.
          The created user will have the ability to create databases and will not be
          able to create new users.</para>
        </section>
        
        <section>
          <title>Configure PostgreSQL</title>

          <para>Now, you will need to edit <filename>pg_hba.conf</filename> which is
          usually located in <filename>/var/lib/pgsql/data/</filename>. In this file,
          you will need to add a new line to it as follows:</para>

          <para>
            <computeroutput>host   all    bugs   127.0.0.1    255.255.255.255  md5</computeroutput>
          </para>
          
          <para>This means that for TCP/IP (host) connections, allow connections from
          '127.0.0.1' to 'all' databases on this server from the 'bugs' user, and use
          password authentication (md5) for that user.</para>

          <para>Now, you will need to restart PostgreSQL, but you will need to fully
          stop and start the server rather than just restarting due to the possibility
          of a change to <filename>postgresql.conf</filename>. After the server has
          restarted, you will need to edit <filename>localconfig</filename>, finding
          the <literal>$db_driver</literal> variable and setting it to
          <literal>Pg</literal> and changing the password in <literal>$db_pass</literal>
          to the one you picked previously, while setting up the account.</para> 
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>  

    <section>
      <title>checksetup.pl</title>

      <para>
        Next, rerun <filename>checksetup.pl</filename>. It reconfirms
        that all the modules are present, and notices the altered 
        localconfig file, which it assumes you have edited to your
        satisfaction. It compiles the UI templates,
        connects to the database using the 'bugs'
        user you created and the password you defined, and creates the 
        'bugs' database and the tables therein. 
      </para>

      <para>
        After that, it asks for details of an administrator account. Bugzilla
        can have multiple administrators - you can create more later - but
        it needs one to start off with.
        Enter the email address of an administrator, his or her full name, 
        and a suitable Bugzilla password.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        <filename>checksetup.pl</filename> will then finish. You may rerun
        <filename>checksetup.pl</filename> at any time if you wish.
      </para>
    </section>


    <section id="http">
      <title>Web server</title>
      <para>
        Configure your web server according to the instructions in the
        appropriate section. (If it makes a difference in your choice,
        the Bugzilla Team recommends Apache.) To check whether your web server
	is correctly configured, try to access <filename>testagent.cgi</filename>
	from your web server. If "OK" is displayed, then your configuration
	is successful. Regardless of which web server
        you are using, however, ensure that sensitive information is
        not remotely available by properly applying the access controls in
        <xref linkend="security-webserver-access"/>. You can run
        <filename>testserver.pl</filename> to check if your web server serves
        Bugzilla files as expected.
      </para>

      <section id="http-apache">
        <title>Bugzilla using Apache</title>
        <para>You have two options for running Bugzilla under Apache - 
          <link linkend="http-apache-mod_cgi">mod_cgi</link> (the default) and
          <link linkend="http-apache-mod_perl">mod_perl</link> (new in Bugzilla
          2.23)
        </para>
        <section id="http-apache-mod_cgi">
            <title>Apache <productname>httpd</productname> with mod_cgi</title>
    
            <para>
            To configure your Apache web server to work with Bugzilla while using
            mod_cgi, do the following:
            </para>
            
            <procedure>
            <step>
                <para>
                Load <filename>httpd.conf</filename> in your editor.
                In Fedora and Red Hat Linux, this file is found in
                <filename class="directory">/etc/httpd/conf</filename>.
                </para>
            </step>
    
            <step>
                <para>
                Apache uses <computeroutput>&lt;Directory&gt;</computeroutput>
                directives to permit fine-grained permission setting. Add the
                following lines to a directive that applies to the location
                of your Bugzilla installation. (If such a section does not
                exist, you'll want to add one.) In this example, Bugzilla has
                been installed at 
                <filename class="directory">/var/www/html/bugzilla</filename>.
                </para>
    
                <programlisting>
    &lt;Directory /var/www/html/bugzilla&gt;
    AddHandler cgi-script .cgi
    Options +Indexes +ExecCGI
    DirectoryIndex index.cgi
    AllowOverride Limit
    &lt;/Directory&gt;
                </programlisting>
    
                <para>
                These instructions: allow apache to run .cgi files found
                within the bugzilla directory; instructs the server to look
                for a file called <filename>index.cgi</filename> if someone
                only types the directory name into the browser; and allows
                Bugzilla's <filename>.htaccess</filename> files to override
                global permissions.
                </para>
    
                <note>
                <para>
                    It is possible to make these changes globally, or to the
                    directive controlling Bugzilla's parent directory (e.g.
                    <computeroutput>&lt;Directory /var/www/html/&gt;</computeroutput>).
                    Such changes would also apply to the Bugzilla directory...
                    but they would also apply to many other places where they
                    may or may not be appropriate. In most cases, including
                    this one, it is better to be as restrictive as possible
                    when granting extra access.
                </para>
                </note>
            </step>                    
    
            <step>
                <para>
                <filename>checksetup.pl</filename> can set tighter permissions
                on Bugzilla's files and directories if it knows what group the
                webserver runs as. Find the <computeroutput>Group</computeroutput>
                line in <filename>httpd.conf</filename>, place the value found
                there in the <replaceable>$webservergroup</replaceable> variable
                in <filename>localconfig</filename>, then rerun
                <filename>checksetup.pl</filename>.
                </para>
            </step>
    
            <step>
                <para>
                Optional: If Bugzilla does not actually reside in the webspace
                directory, but instead has been symbolically linked there, you
                will need to add the following to the
                <computeroutput>Options</computeroutput> line of the Bugzilla 
                <computeroutput>&lt;Directory&gt;</computeroutput> directive
                (the same one as in the step above):
                </para>
    
                <programlisting>
    +FollowSymLinks
                </programlisting>
    
                <para>
                Without this directive, Apache will not follow symbolic links
                to places outside its own directory structure, and you will be
                unable to run Bugzilla.
                </para>
            </step>
            </procedure>
        </section>
        <section id="http-apache-mod_perl">
            <title>Apache <productname>httpd</productname> with mod_perl</title>
            
            <para>Some configuration is required to make Bugzilla work with Apache
            and mod_perl</para>
            
            <procedure>
            <step>
                <para>
                Load <filename>httpd.conf</filename> in your editor.
                In Fedora and Red Hat Linux, this file is found in
                <filename class="directory">/etc/httpd/conf</filename>.
                </para>
            </step>
            
            <step>
                <para>Add the following information to your httpd.conf file, substituting
                where appropriate with your own local paths.</para>
                
                <note>
                <para>This should be used instead of the &lt;Directory&gt; block
                shown above. This should also be above any other <literal>mod_perl</literal>
                directives within the <filename>httpd.conf</filename> and must be specified
                in the order as below.</para>
                </note>
                <warning>
                <para>You should also ensure that you have disabled <literal>KeepAlive</literal>
                support in your Apache install when utilizing Bugzilla under mod_perl</para>
                </warning> 
                
                <programlisting>
    PerlSwitches -I/var/www/html/bugzilla -w -T
    PerlConfigRequire /var/www/html/bugzilla/mod_perl.pl
                </programlisting>
            </step>
			
			<step>
				<para>
					<filename>checksetup.pl</filename> can set tighter permissions
					on Bugzilla's files and directories if it knows what group the
					webserver runs as. Find the <computeroutput>Group</computeroutput>
					line in <filename>httpd.conf</filename>, place the value found
					there in the <replaceable>$webservergroup</replaceable> variable
					in <filename>localconfig</filename>, then rerun
					<filename>checksetup.pl</filename>.
				</para>
            </step>
            </procedure>
            
            <para>On restarting Apache, Bugzilla should now be running within the
            mod_perl environment. Please ensure you have run checksetup.pl to set
		    permissions before you restart Apache.</para>
        
            <note>
            <para>Please bear the following points in mind when looking at using 
                Bugzilla under mod_perl: 
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                <para>
                    mod_perl support in Bugzilla can take up a HUGE amount of RAM. You could be
                    looking at 30MB per httpd child, easily. Basically, you just need a lot of RAM.
                    The more RAM you can get, the better. mod_perl is basically trading RAM for
                    speed. At least 2GB total system RAM is recommended for running Bugzilla under
                    mod_perl.
                </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                <para>
                    Under mod_perl, you have to restart Apache if you make any manual change to
                    any Bugzilla file. You can't just reload--you have to actually 
					<emphasis>restart</emphasis> the server (as in make sure it stops and starts 
					again). You <emphasis>can</emphasis> change localconfig and the params file 
					manually, if you want, because those are re-read every time you load a page.
                </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                <para>
                    You must run in Apache's Prefork MPM (this is the default). The Worker MPM
                    may not work--we haven't tested Bugzilla's mod_perl support under threads.
					(And, in fact, we're fairly sure it <emphasis>won't</emphasis> work.)
                </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                <para>
                    Bugzilla generally expects to be the only mod_perl application running on
                    your entire server. It may or may not work if there are other applications also
                    running under mod_perl. It does try its best to play nice with other mod_perl
                    applications, but it still may have conflicts.
                </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                <para>
                    It is recommended that you have one Bugzilla instance running under mod_perl
                    on your server. Bugzilla has not been tested with more than one instance running.
                </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            </note>
        </section>
      </section>
      
      <section id="http-iis">
        <title>Microsoft <productname>Internet Information Services</productname></title>

        <para>
          If you are running Bugzilla on Windows and choose to use
          Microsoft's <productname>Internet Information Services</productname>
          or <productname>Personal Web Server</productname> you will need
          to perform a number of other configuration steps as explained below.
          You may also want to refer to the following Microsoft Knowledge
          Base articles: 
          <ulink url="http://support.microsoft.com/default.aspx?scid=kb;en-us;245225">245225</ulink> 
          <quote>HOW TO: Configure and Test a PERL Script with IIS 4.0,
          5.0, and 5.1</quote> (for <productname>Internet Information
          Services</productname>) and 
          <ulink url="http://support.microsoft.com/default.aspx?scid=kb;en-us;231998">231998</ulink>          
          <quote>HOW TO: FP2000: How to Use Perl with Microsoft Personal Web
          Server on Windows 95/98</quote> (for <productname>Personal Web
          Server</productname>).
        </para>

        <para>
          You will need to create a virtual directory for the Bugzilla
          install.  Put the Bugzilla files in a directory that is named
          something <emphasis>other</emphasis> than what you want your
          end-users accessing.  That is, if you want your users to access
          your Bugzilla installation through 
          <quote>http://&lt;yourdomainname&gt;/Bugzilla</quote>, then do
          <emphasis>not</emphasis> put your Bugzilla files in a directory
          named <quote>Bugzilla</quote>.  Instead, place them in a different
          location, and then use the IIS Administration tool to create a
          Virtual Directory named "Bugzilla" that acts as an alias for the
          actual location of the files.  When creating that virtual directory,
          make sure you add the <quote>Execute (such as ISAPI applications or
          CGI)</quote> access permission.
        </para>

        <para>
          You will also need to tell IIS how to handle Bugzilla's
          .cgi files. Using the IIS Administration tool again, open up
          the properties for the new virtual directory and select the
          Configuration option to access the Script Mappings. Create an
          entry mapping .cgi to:
        </para>

        <programlisting>
&lt;full path to perl.exe &gt;\perl.exe -x&lt;full path to Bugzilla&gt; -wT "%s" %s
        </programlisting>

        <para>
          For example:
        </para>

        <programlisting>
c:\perl\bin\perl.exe -xc:\bugzilla -wT "%s" %s
        </programlisting>

        <note>
          <para>
            The ActiveState install may have already created an entry for
            .pl files that is limited to <quote>GET,HEAD,POST</quote>. If
            so, this mapping should be <emphasis>removed</emphasis> as
            Bugzilla's .pl files are not designed to be run via a webserver.
          </para>
        </note>

        <para>
          IIS will also need to know that the index.cgi should be treated
          as a default document.  On the Documents tab page of the virtual
          directory properties, you need to add index.cgi as a default
          document type.  If you  wish, you may remove the other default
          document types for this particular virtual directory, since Bugzilla 
          doesn't use any of them.
        </para>

        <para>
          Also, and this can't be stressed enough, make sure that files
          such as <filename>localconfig</filename> and your
          <filename class="directory">data</filename> directory are
          secured as described in <xref linkend="security-webserver-access"/>.
        </para>

      </section>

    </section>
    
    <section id="install-config-bugzilla">
      <title>Bugzilla</title>
      
      <para>
        Your Bugzilla should now be working. Access 
        <filename>http://&lt;your-bugzilla-server&gt;/</filename> - 
        you should see the Bugzilla
        front page. If not, consult the Troubleshooting section,
        <xref linkend="troubleshooting"/>.
      </para>

      <note>
        <para>
          The URL above may be incorrect if you installed Bugzilla into a 
          subdirectory or used a symbolic link from your web site root to 
          the Bugzilla directory.
        </para>
      </note>
      
      <para>
        Log in with the administrator account you defined in the last 
        <filename>checksetup.pl</filename> run. You should go through 
        the parameters on the Edit Parameters page
        (see link in the footer) and see if there are any you wish to
        change. 
        They key parameters are documented in <xref linkend="parameters"/>;
        you should certainly alter 
        <command>maintainer</command> and <command>urlbase</command>; 
        you may also want to alter 
        <command>cookiepath</command> or <command>requirelogin</command>.
      </para>

      <para>
        This would also be a good time to revisit the
        <filename>localconfig</filename> file and make sure that the 
        names of the priorities, severities, platforms and operating systems
        are those you wish to use when you start creating bugs. Remember
        to rerun <filename>checksetup.pl</filename> if you change it.
      </para>

      <para>
        Bugzilla has several optional features which require extra 
        configuration. You can read about those in
        <xref linkend="extraconfig"/>.
      </para>
    </section> 
  </section>


  <section id="extraconfig">
    <title>Optional Additional Configuration</title>

    <para>
      Bugzilla has a number of optional features. This section describes how
      to configure or enable them.
    </para>
    
    <section>
      <title>Bug Graphs</title>

      <para>If you have installed the necessary Perl modules you
      can start collecting statistics for the nifty Bugzilla 
      graphs.</para>

      <screen><prompt>bash#</prompt> <command>crontab -e</command></screen>

      <para>
        This should bring up the crontab file in your editor. 
        Add a cron entry like this to run 
        <filename>collectstats.pl</filename> 
        daily at 5 after midnight:
      </para>
      
      <programlisting>5 0 * * * cd &lt;your-bugzilla-directory&gt; ; ./collectstats.pl</programlisting>

      <para>
        After two days have passed you'll be able to view bug graphs from
        the Reports page.
      </para>

      <para>
        When upgrading Bugzilla, this format may change.
        To create new status data, (re)move old data and run the following 
        commands:
      </para>

      <screen>
        <prompt>bash$</prompt>
        <command>cd &lt;your-bugzilla-directory&gt;</command>
        <prompt>bash$</prompt>
        <command>./collectstats.pl --regenerate</command>
      </screen>

      <note>
        <para>
          Windows does not have 'cron', but it does have the Task
          Scheduler, which performs the same duties. There are also
          third-party tools that can be used to implement cron, such as
          <ulink url="http://www.nncron.ru/">nncron</ulink>.
        </para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Dependency Charts</title>

      <para>As well as the text-based dependency trees, Bugzilla also
      supports a graphical view of dependency relationships, using a 
      package called 'dot'.
      Exactly how this works is controlled by the 'webdotbase' parameter,
      which can have one of three values:
      </para>

      <para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            A complete file path to the command 'dot' (part of 
            <ulink url="http://www.graphviz.org/">GraphViz</ulink>) 
            will generate the graphs locally
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            A URL prefix pointing to an installation of the webdot package will
            generate the graphs remotely
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            A blank value will disable dependency graphing.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </para>
      
      <para>The easiest way to get this working is to install
      <ulink url="http://www.graphviz.org/">GraphViz</ulink>. If you
      do that, you need to
      <ulink url="http://httpd.apache.org/docs/mod/mod_imap.html">enable
      server-side image maps</ulink> in Apache.
      Alternatively, you could set up a webdot server, or use the AT&amp;T 
      public webdot server. This is the default for the webdotbase param, 
      but it's often overloaded and slow. Note that AT&amp;T's server 
      won't work
      if Bugzilla is only accessible using HARTS. 
      <emphasis>Editor's note: What the heck is HARTS? Google doesn't know...
      </emphasis>
      </para>
   </section>

    <section id="installation-whining-cron">
      <title>The Whining Cron</title>

      <para>What good are
      bugs if they're not annoying? To help make them more so you
      can set up Bugzilla's automatic whining system to complain at engineers
      which leave their bugs in the NEW or REOPENED state without triaging them.
      </para>
      <para>
        This can be done by adding the following command as a daily
        crontab entry, in the same manner as explained above for bug
        graphs. This example runs it at 12.55am. 
      </para>

      <programlisting>55 0 * * * cd &lt;your-bugzilla-directory&gt; ; ./whineatnews.pl</programlisting>

      <note>
        <para>
          Windows does not have 'cron', but it does have the Task
          Scheduler, which performs the same duties. There are also
          third-party tools that can be used to implement cron, such as
          <ulink url="http://www.nncron.ru/">nncron</ulink>.
        </para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section id="installation-whining">
      <title>Whining</title>

      <para>
        As of Bugzilla 2.20, users can configure Bugzilla to regularly annoy 
        them at regular intervals, by having Bugzilla execute saved searches
        at certain times and emailing the results to the user.  This is known
        as "Whining".  The process of configuring Whining is described 
        in <xref linkend="whining"/>, but for it to work a Perl script must be
        executed at regular intervals.
      </para>

      <para>
        This can be done by adding the following command as a daily
        crontab entry, in the same manner as explained above for bug
        graphs. This example runs it every 15 minutes. 
      </para>

      <programlisting>*/15 * * * * cd &lt;your-bugzilla-directory&gt; ; ./whine.pl</programlisting>

      <note>
        <para>
          Whines can be executed as often as every 15 minutes, so if you specify
          longer intervals between executions of whine.pl, some users may not 
          be whined at as often as they would expect.  Depending on the person,
          this can either be a very Good Thing or a very Bad Thing.
        </para>
      </note>

      <note>
        <para>
          Windows does not have 'cron', but it does have the Task
          Scheduler, which performs the same duties. There are also
          third-party tools that can be used to implement cron, such as
          <ulink url="http://www.nncron.ru/">nncron</ulink>.
        </para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section id="patch-viewer">
      <title>Patch Viewer</title>
      
      <para>
        Patch Viewer is the engine behind Bugzilla's graphical display of
        code patches. You can integrate this with copies of the
        <filename>cvs</filename>, <filename>lxr</filename> and
        <filename>bonsai</filename> tools if you have them, by giving
        the locations of your installation of these tools in
        <filename>editparams.cgi</filename>.
      </para>
        
      <para>
        Patch Viewer also optionally will use the 
        <filename>cvs</filename>, <filename>diff</filename> and 
        <filename>interdiff</filename>
        command-line utilities if they exist on the system.
        Interdiff can be obtained from 
        <ulink url="http://cyberelk.net/tim/patchutils/"/>.
        If these programs are not in the system path, you can configure
        their locations in <filename>localconfig</filename>.
      </para>
      

    </section>
    
    <section id="bzldap">
      <title>LDAP Authentication</title>

      <para>LDAP authentication is a module for Bugzilla's plugin 
      authentication architecture.
      </para>

      <para>
      The existing authentication
      scheme for Bugzilla uses email addresses as the primary user ID, and a
      password to authenticate that user. All places within Bugzilla where
      you need to deal with user ID (e.g assigning a bug) use the email
      address. The LDAP authentication builds on top of this scheme, rather
      than replacing it. The initial log in is done with a username and
      password for the LDAP directory. Bugzilla tries to bind to LDAP using
      those credentials, and if successful, try to map this account to a
      Bugzilla account. If a  LDAP mail attribute is defined, the value of this
      attribute is used, otherwise emailsuffix parameter is appended to LDAP
      username to form a full email address. If an account for this address
      already exists in your Bugzilla system, it will log in to that account.
      If no account for that email address exists, one is created at the time
      of login. (In this case, Bugzilla will attempt to use the "displayName"
      or "cn" attribute to determine the user's full name.) After
      authentication, all other user-related tasks are still handled by email
      address, not LDAP username. You still assign bugs by email address, query
      on users by email address, etc.
      </para>

      <caution>
        <para>Because the Bugzilla account is not created until the first time
        a user logs in, a user who has not yet logged is unknown to Bugzilla.
        This means they cannot be used as an assignee or QA contact (default or
        otherwise), added to any cc list, or any other such operation. One
        possible workaround is the <filename>bugzilla_ldapsync.rb</filename>
        script in the
        <glossterm linkend="gloss-contrib"><filename class="directory">contrib</filename></glossterm> directory. Another possible solution is fixing
        <ulink url="http://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=201069">bug
        201069</ulink>.
        </para>
      </caution>

      <para>Parameters required to use LDAP Authentication:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry id="param-user_verify_class">
          <term>user_verify_class</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>This parameter should be set to <quote>LDAP</quote>
            <emphasis>only</emphasis> if you will be using an LDAP directory
            for authentication. If you set this param to <quote>LDAP</quote> but
            fail to set up the other parameters listed below you will not be
            able to log back in to Bugzilla one you log out. If this happens
            to you, you will need to manually edit
            <filename>data/params</filename> and set user_verify_class to
            <quote>DB</quote>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry id="param-LDAPserver">
          <term>LDAPserver</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>This parameter should be set to the name (and optionally the
            port) of your LDAP server. If no port is specified, it assumes
            the default LDAP port of 389.
            </para>
            <para>Ex. <quote>ldap.company.com</quote>
             or <quote>ldap.company.com:3268</quote>
            </para>
            <para>You can also specify a LDAP URI, so as to use other
            protocols, such as LDAPS or LDAPI. If port was not specified in
            the URI, the default is either 389 or 636 for 'LDAP' and 'LDAPS'
            schemes respectively.
            </para>
            <para>Ex. <quote>ldap://ldap.company.com</quote>,
            <quote>ldaps://ldap.company.com</quote> or
            <quote>ldapi://%2fvar%2flib%2fldap_sock</quote>
            </para>
           </listitem>
         </varlistentry>

         <varlistentry id="param-LDAPbinddn">
           <term>LDAPbinddn [Optional]</term>
           <listitem>
             <para>Some LDAP servers will not allow an anonymous bind to search
             the directory. If this is the case with your configuration you
             should set the LDAPbinddn parameter to the user account Bugzilla
             should use instead of the anonymous bind.
             </para>
             <para>Ex. <quote>cn=default,cn=user:password</quote></para>
           </listitem>
         </varlistentry>

         <varlistentry id="param-LDAPBaseDN">
           <term>LDAPBaseDN</term>
           <listitem>
             <para>The LDAPBaseDN parameter should be set to the location in
             your LDAP tree that you would like to search for email addresses.
             Your uids should be unique under the DN specified here.
             </para>
             <para>Ex. <quote>ou=People,o=Company</quote></para>
           </listitem>
         </varlistentry>

         <varlistentry id="param-LDAPuidattribute">
           <term>LDAPuidattribute</term>
           <listitem>
             <para>The LDAPuidattribute parameter should be set to the attribute
             which contains the unique UID of your users. The value retrieved
             from this attribute will be used when attempting to bind as the
             user to confirm their password.
             </para>
             <para>Ex. <quote>uid</quote></para>
           </listitem>
         </varlistentry>

         <varlistentry id="param-LDAPmailattribute">
           <term>LDAPmailattribute</term>
           <listitem>
             <para>The LDAPmailattribute parameter should be the name of the
             attribute which contains the email address your users will enter
             into the Bugzilla login boxes.
             </para>
             <para>Ex. <quote>mail</quote></para>
           </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

    </section>
    
    <section id="apache-addtype">
      <title>Serving Alternate Formats with the right MIME type</title>

      <para>
        Some Bugzilla pages have alternate formats, other than just plain
        <acronym>HTML</acronym>. In particular, a few Bugzilla pages can 
        output their contents as either <acronym>XUL</acronym> (a special 
        Mozilla format, that looks like a program <acronym>GUI</acronym>) 
        or <acronym>RDF</acronym> (a type of structured <acronym>XML</acronym> 
        that can be read by various programs).
      </para>
      <para>
        In order for your users to see these pages correctly, Apache must 
        send them with the right <acronym>MIME</acronym> type. To do this, 
        add the following lines to your Apache configuration, either in the 
        <computeroutput>&lt;VirtualHost&gt;</computeroutput> section for your
        Bugzilla, or in the <computeroutput>&lt;Directory&gt;</computeroutput>
        section for your Bugzilla:
      </para>
      <para>
        <screen>AddType application/vnd.mozilla.xul+xml .xul
AddType application/rdf+xml .rdf</screen>
      </para>
    </section>    
  </section>

  <section id="multiple-bz-dbs">
    <title>Multiple Bugzilla databases with a single installation</title>

    <para>The previous instructions referred to a standard installation, with
      one unique Bugzilla database. However, you may want to host several
      distinct installations, without having several copies of the code. This is
      possible by using the PROJECT environment variable. When accessed,
      Bugzilla checks for the existence of this variable, and if present, uses
      its value to check for an alternative configuration file named
      <filename>localconfig.&lt;PROJECT&gt;</filename> in the same location as
      the default one (<filename>localconfig</filename>). It also checks for
      customized templates in a directory named
      <filename>&lt;PROJECT&gt;</filename> in the same location as the
      default one (<filename>template/&lt;langcode&gt;</filename>). By default
      this is <filename>template/en/default</filename> so PROJECT's templates
      would be located at <filename>template/en/PROJECT</filename>.</para> 

      <para>To set up an alternate installation, just export PROJECT=foo before
      running <command>checksetup.pl</command> for the first time. It will
      result in a file called <filename>localconfig.foo</filename> instead of
      <filename>localconfig</filename>. Edit this file as described above, with
      reference to a new database, and re-run <command>checksetup.pl</command>
      to populate it. That's all.</para>

    <para>Now you have to configure the web server to pass this environment
      variable when accessed via an alternate URL, such as virtual host for
      instance. The following is an example of how you could do it in Apache,
      other Webservers may differ.
<programlisting>
&lt;VirtualHost 212.85.153.228:80&gt;
    ServerName foo.bar.baz
    SetEnv PROJECT foo
    Alias /bugzilla /var/www/bugzilla
&lt;/VirtualHost&gt;
</programlisting>
    </para>

    <para>Don't forget to also export this variable before accessing Bugzilla
       by other means, such as cron tasks for instance.</para> 
  </section>

  <section id="os-specific">
    <title>OS-Specific Installation Notes</title>

    <para>Many aspects of the Bugzilla installation can be affected by the
    operating system you choose to install it on. Sometimes it can be made
    easier and others more difficult. This section will attempt to help you
    understand both the difficulties of running on specific operating systems
    and the utilities available to make it easier.
    </para>

    <para>If you have anything to add or notes for an operating system not
    covered, please file a bug in &bzg-bugs;. 
    </para>

    <section id="os-win32">
      <title>Microsoft Windows</title>
      <para>
        Making Bugzilla work on Windows is more difficult than making it
        work on Unix.  For that reason, we still recommend doing so on a Unix 
        based system such as GNU/Linux.  That said, if you do want to get
        Bugzilla running on Windows, you will need to make the following
        adjustments. A detailed step-by-step
        <ulink url="http://www.bugzilla.org/docs/win32install.html">
        installation guide for Windows</ulink> is also available
        if you need more help with your installation.
      </para>

      <section id="win32-perl">
        <title>Win32 Perl</title>
        <para>
          Perl for Windows can be obtained from 
          <ulink url="http://www.activestate.com/">ActiveState</ulink>.
           You should be able to find a compiled binary at <ulink 
           url="http://aspn.activestate.com/ASPN/Downloads/ActivePerl/" />.
           The following instructions assume that you are using version
           5.8.1 of ActiveState.
          </para>
        </section>
  
      <section id="win32-perl-modules">
        <title>Perl Modules on Win32</title>

        <para>
          Bugzilla on Windows requires the same perl modules found in
          <xref linkend="install-perlmodules"/>. The main difference is that
          windows uses <glossterm linkend="gloss-ppm">PPM</glossterm> instead
          of CPAN.
        </para>

        <programlisting>
C:\perl&gt; <command>ppm install &lt;module name&gt;</command>
        </programlisting>

        <para>
          The best source for the Windows PPM modules needed for Bugzilla
          is probably the Bugzilla Test Server (aka 'Landfill'), so 
          you should add the Landfill package repository as follows:
        </para>

        <programlisting>
<command>ppm repository add landfill http://www.landfill.bugzilla.org/ppm/</command>
        </programlisting>

        <note>
          <para>
            The PPM repository stores modules in 'packages' that may have
            a slightly different name than the module.  If retrieving these
            modules from there, you will need to pay attention to the information
            provided when you run <command>checksetup.pl</command> as it will
            tell you what package you'll need to install.
          </para>
        </note>

        <tip>
          <para>
            If you are behind a corporate firewall, you will need to let the
            ActiveState PPM utility know how to get through it to access
            the repositories by setting the HTTP_proxy system environmental
            variable. For more information on setting that variable, see
            the ActiveState documentation.
          </para>
        </tip>
      </section>
  
      <section id="win32-code-changes">
        <title>Code changes required to run on Win32</title>

        <para>
          Bugzilla on Win32 is supported out of the box from version 2.20; this
          means that no code changes are required to get Bugzilla running.
        </para>
        
      </section>

      <section id="win32-http">
        <title>Serving the web pages</title>

        <para>
          As is the case on Unix based systems, any web server should
          be able to handle Bugzilla; however, the Bugzilla Team still
          recommends Apache whenever asked. No matter what web server
          you choose, be sure to pay attention to the security notes
          in <xref linkend="security-webserver-access"/>. More
          information on configuring specific web servers can be found
          in <xref linkend="http"/>.
        </para>

        <note>
          <para>
            If using Apache on windows, you can set the <ulink
            url="http://httpd.apache.org/docs-2.0/mod/core.html#scriptinterpretersource">ScriptInterpreterSource</ulink>
            directive in your Apache config to avoid having to modify
            the first line of every script to contain your path to Perl
            instead of <filename>/usr/bin/perl</filename>. When setting
            <filename>ScriptInterpreterSource</filename>, do not forget
            to specify the <command>-T</command> flag to enable the taint
            mode. For example: <command>C:\Perl\bin\perl.exe -T</command>.
          </para>
        </note>

      </section>
      
      <section id="win32-email">
        <title>Sending Email</title>

        <para>
          To enable Bugzilla to send email on Windows, the server running the
          Bugzilla code must be able to connect to, or act as, an SMTP server.
        </para>
        
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="os-macosx">
      <title><productname>Mac OS X</productname></title>

      <para>Making Bugzilla work on Mac OS X requires the following 
      adjustments.</para>

      <section id="macosx-sendmail">
        <title>Sendmail</title>

        <para>In Mac OS X 10.3 and later, 
        <ulink url="http://www.postfix.org/">Postfix</ulink> 
        is used as the built-in email server.  Postfix provides an executable
        that mimics sendmail enough to fool Bugzilla, as long as Bugzilla can 
        find it.</para>

        <para>As of version 2.20, Bugzilla will be able to find the fake 
        sendmail executable without any assistance.  However, you will have 
        to turn on the sendmailnow parameter before you do anything that would 
        result in email being sent.  For more information, see the description 
        of the sendmailnow parameter in <xref linkend="parameters"/>.</para>

      </section>

      <section id="macosx-libraries">
        <title>Libraries &amp; Perl Modules on Mac OS X</title>

        <para>Apple did not include the GD library with Mac OS X. Bugzilla
        needs this for bug graphs.</para>

        <para>You can install it using a program called
        Fink, which is similar in nature to the CPAN installer, but installs
        common GNU utilities. Fink is available from
        <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/fink/"/>.</para>

        <para>Follow the instructions for setting up Fink. Once it's installed,
        you'll want to use it to install the <filename>gd2</filename> package.
        </para>

        <para>It will prompt you for a number of dependencies, type 'y' and hit
        enter to install all of the dependencies and then watch it work. You will
        then be able to use <glossterm linkend="gloss-cpan">CPAN</glossterm> to
        install the GD Perl module.
        </para>

        <note>
          <para>To prevent creating conflicts with the software that Apple
          installs by default, Fink creates its own directory tree at 
          <filename class="directory">/sw</filename> where it installs most of
          the software that it installs. This means your libraries and headers
          will be at <filename class="directory">/sw/lib</filename> and
          <filename class="directory">/sw/include</filename> instead of
          <filename class="directory">/usr/lib</filename> and
          <filename class="directory">/usr/include</filename>. When the
          Perl module config script asks where your <filename>libgd</filename>
          is, be sure to tell it
          <filename class="directory">/sw/lib</filename>.
          </para>
        </note>

        <para>Also available via Fink is <filename>expat</filename>. After using
        fink to install the expat package you will be able to install
        XML::Parser using CPAN. There is one caveat. Unlike recent versions of
        the GD module, XML::Parser doesn't prompt for the location of the
        required libraries. When using CPAN, you will need to use the following
        command sequence:
        </para>

        <screen>
# perl -MCPAN -e'look XML::Parser'        <co id="macosx-look"/>
# perl Makefile.PL EXPATLIBPATH=/sw/lib EXPATINCPATH=/sw/include
# make; make test; make install           <co id="macosx-make"/>
# exit                                    <co id="macosx-exit"/>
        </screen>
        <calloutlist>
          <callout arearefs="macosx-look macosx-exit">
            <para>The look command will download the module and spawn a
            new shell with the extracted files as the current working directory.
            The exit command will return you to your original shell.
            </para>
          </callout>
          <callout arearefs="macosx-make">
            <para>You should watch the output from these make commands,
            especially <quote>make test</quote> as errors may prevent 
            XML::Parser from functioning correctly with Bugzilla.
            </para>
          </callout>
        </calloutlist>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="os-linux">
      <title>Linux Distributions</title>
            <para>Many Linux distributions include Bugzilla and its 
            dependencies in their native package management systems. 
            Installing Bugzilla with root access on any Linux system 
            should be as simple as finding the Bugzilla package in the 
            package management application and installing it using the 
            normal command syntax. Several distributions also perform 
            the proper web server configuration automatically on installation.
            </para>
            <para>Please consult the documentation of your Linux 
            distribution for instructions on how to install packages, 
            or for specific instructions on installing Bugzilla with 
            native package management tools. There is also a 
            <ulink url="http://wiki.mozilla.org/Bugzilla:Linux_Distro_Installation">
            Bugzilla Wiki Page</ulink> for distro-specific installation
            notes.
            </para>
    </section>
  </section>


  <section id="nonroot">
    <title>UNIX (non-root) Installation Notes</title>

    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <para>If you are running a *NIX OS as non-root, either due
      to lack of access (web hosts, for example) or for security
      reasons, this will detail how to install Bugzilla on such
      a setup. It is recommended that you read through the
      <xref linkend="installation" />
      first to get an idea on the installation steps required.
      (These notes will reference to steps in that guide.)</para>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>MySQL</title>

      <para>You may have MySQL installed as root. If you're
      setting up an account with a web host, a MySQL account
      needs to be set up for you. From there, you can create
      the bugs account, or use the account given to you.</para>

      <warning>
        <para>You may have problems trying to set up
        <command>GRANT</command> permissions to the database.
        If you're using a web host, chances are that you have a
        separate database which is already locked down (or one big
        database with limited/no access to the other areas), but you
        may want to ask your system administrator what the security
        settings are set to, and/or run the <command>GRANT</command>
        command for you.</para>

        <para>Also, you will probably not be able to change the MySQL
        root user password (for obvious reasons), so skip that
        step.</para>
      </warning>

      <section>
        <title>Running MySQL as Non-Root</title>
          <section>
            <title>The Custom Configuration Method</title>
              <para>Create a file .my.cnf in your 
              home directory (using /home/foo in this example)
              as follows....</para>
              <programlisting>
[mysqld]
datadir=/home/foo/mymysql
socket=/home/foo/mymysql/thesock
port=8081

[mysql]
socket=/home/foo/mymysql/thesock
port=8081

[mysql.server]
user=mysql
basedir=/var/lib

[safe_mysqld]
err-log=/home/foo/mymysql/the.log
pid-file=/home/foo/mymysql/the.pid
              </programlisting>
          </section>
          <section>
            <title>The Custom Built Method</title>
    
            <para>You can install MySQL as a not-root, if you really need to.
            Build it with PREFIX set to <filename class="directory">/home/foo/mysql</filename>,
            or use pre-installed executables, specifying that you want
            to put all of the data files in <filename class="directory">/home/foo/mysql/data</filename>.
            If there is another MySQL server running on the system that you
            do not own, use the -P option to specify a TCP port that is not
            in use.</para>
          </section>
    
          <section>
            <title>Starting the Server</title>
            <para>After your mysqld program is built and any .my.cnf file is 
            in place, you must initialize the databases (ONCE).</para>
            <screen>
              <prompt>bash$</prompt>
              <command>mysql_install_db</command>
            </screen>
            <para>Then start the daemon with</para>
            <screen>
              <prompt>bash$</prompt>
              <command>safe_mysql &amp;</command>
            </screen>
            <para>After you start mysqld the first time, you then connect to
            it as "root" and <command>GRANT</command> permissions to other
            users. (Again, the MySQL root account has nothing to do with
            the *NIX root account.)</para>
    
            <note>
              <para>You will need to start the daemons yourself. You can either
              ask your system administrator to add them to system startup files, or
              add a crontab entry that runs a script to check on these daemons
              and restart them if needed.</para>
            </note>
    
            <warning>
              <para>Do NOT run daemons or other services on a server without first
              consulting your system administrator! Daemons use up system resources
              and running one may be in violation of your terms of service for any
              machine on which you are a user!</para>
            </warning>
          </section>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Perl</title>

      <para>On the extremely rare chance that you don't have Perl on
      the machine, you will have to build the sources
      yourself. The following commands should get your system
      installed with your own personal version of Perl:</para>

      <screen>
        <prompt>bash$</prompt>
        <command>wget http://perl.com/CPAN/src/stable.tar.gz</command>
        <prompt>bash$</prompt>
        <command>tar zvxf stable.tar.gz</command>
        <prompt>bash$</prompt>
        <command>cd perl-5.8.1</command> (or whatever the version of Perl is called)
        <prompt>bash$</prompt>
        <command>sh Configure -de -Dprefix=/home/foo/perl</command>
        <prompt>bash$</prompt>
        <command>make &amp;&amp; make test &amp;&amp; make install</command>
      </screen>

      <para>Once you have Perl installed into a directory (probably
      in <filename class="directory">~/perl/bin</filename>), you'll have to
      change the locations on the scripts, which is detailed later on
      this page.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="install-perlmodules-nonroot">
      <title>Perl Modules</title>

      <para>Installing the Perl modules as a non-root user is probably the
      hardest part of the process. There are two different methods: a
      completely independant Perl with its own modules, or personal
      modules using the current (root installed) version of Perl. The
      independant method takes up quite a bit of disk space, but is
      less complex, while the mixed method only uses as much space as the
      modules themselves, but takes more work to setup.</para>

      <section>
        <title>The Independant Method</title>

        <para>The independant method requires that you install your own
        personal version of Perl, as detailed in the previous section. Once
        installed, you can start the CPAN shell with the following
        command:</para>

        <para>
          <screen>
            <prompt>bash$</prompt>
            <command>/home/foo/perl/bin/perl -MCPAN -e 'shell'</command>
          </screen>
        </para>

        <para>And then:</para>

        <para>
          <screen>
            <prompt>cpan&gt;</prompt>
            <command>install Bundle::Bugzilla</command>
          </screen>
        </para>

        <para>With this method, module installation will usually go a lot
        smoother, but if you have any hang-ups, you can consult the next
        section.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>The Mixed Method</title>

        <para>First, you'll need to configure CPAN to
        install modules in your home directory. The CPAN FAQ says the
        following on this issue:</para>

        <para>
          <programlisting>
5)  I am not root, how can I install a module in a personal directory?

    You will most probably like something like this:

      o conf makepl_arg "LIB=~/myperl/lib \
                         INSTALLMAN1DIR=~/myperl/man/man1 \
                         INSTALLMAN3DIR=~/myperl/man/man3"
    install Sybase::Sybperl

    You can make this setting permanent like all "o conf" settings with "o conf commit".

    You will have to add ~/myperl/man to the MANPATH environment variable and also tell your Perl programs to
    look into ~/myperl/lib, e.g. by including

      use lib "$ENV{HOME}/myperl/lib";

    or setting the PERL5LIB environment variable.

    Another thing you should bear in mind is that the UNINST parameter should never be set if you are not root.</programlisting>
        </para>

        <para>So, you will need to create a Perl directory in your home
        directory, as well as the <filename class="directory">lib</filename>,
        <filename class="directory">man</filename>,
        <filename class="directory">man/man1</filename>, and
        <filename class="directory">man/man3</filename> directories in that
        Perl directory. Set the MANPATH variable and PERL5LIB variable, so
        that the installation of the modules goes smoother. (Setting
        UNINST=0 in your "make install" options, on the CPAN first-time
        configuration, is also a good idea.)</para>

        <para>After that, go into the CPAN shell:</para>

        <para>
          <screen>
            <prompt>bash$</prompt>
            <command>perl -MCPAN -e 'shell'</command>
          </screen>
        </para>

        <para>From there, you will need to type in the above "o conf" command
        and commit the changes. Then you can run through the installation:</para>

        <para>
          <screen>
            <prompt>cpan&gt;</prompt>
            <command>install Bundle::Bugzilla</command>
          </screen>
        </para>

        <para>Most of the module installation process should go smoothly. However,
        you may have some problems with Template. When you first start, you will
        want to try to install Template with the XS Stash options on. If this
        doesn't work, it may spit out C compiler error messages and croak back
        to the CPAN shell prompt. So, redo the install, and turn it off. (In fact,
        say no to all of the Template questions.) It may also start failing on a
        few of the tests. If the total tests passed is a reasonable figure (90+%),
        force the install with the following command:</para>

        <para>
          <screen>
            <prompt>cpan&gt;</prompt>
            <command>force install Template</command>
          </screen>
        </para>

        <para>You may also want to install the other optional modules:</para>

        <screen>
          <prompt>cpan&gt;</prompt>
          <command>install GD</command>
          <prompt>cpan&gt;</prompt>
          <command>install Chart::Base</command>
          <prompt>cpan&gt;</prompt>
          <command>install MIME::Parser</command>
        </screen>

      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>HTTP Server</title>

      <para>Ideally, this also needs to be installed as root and
      run under a special webserver account. As long as
      the web server will allow the running of *.cgi files outside of a
      cgi-bin, and a way of denying web access to certain files (such as a
      .htaccess file), you should be good in this department.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Running Apache as Non-Root</title>

        <para>You can run Apache as a non-root user, but the port will need
        to be set to one above 1024. If you type <command>httpd -V</command>,
        you will get a list of the variables that your system copy of httpd
        uses. One of those, namely HTTPD_ROOT, tells you where that
        installation looks for its config information.</para>

        <para>From there, you can copy the config files to your own home
        directory to start editing. When you edit those and then use the -d
        option to override the HTTPD_ROOT compiled into the web server, you
        get control of your own customized web server.</para>

        <note>
          <para>You will need to start the daemons yourself. You can either
          ask your system administrator to add them to system startup files, or
          add a crontab entry that runs a script to check on these daemons
          and restart them if needed.</para>
        </note>

        <warning>
          <para>Do NOT run daemons or other services on a server without first
          consulting your system administrator! Daemons use up system resources
          and running one may be in violation of your terms of service for any
          machine on which you are a user!</para>
        </warning>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Bugzilla</title>

      <para>If you had to install Perl modules as a non-root user
      (<xref linkend="install-perlmodules-nonroot" />) or to non-standard
      directories, you will need to change the scripts, setting the correct
      location of the Perl modules:</para>

      <para>
        <programlisting>perl -pi -e
        's@use strict\;@use strict\; use lib \"/home/foo/perl/lib\"\;@'
        *cgi *pl Bug.pm processmail syncshadowdb</programlisting>

        Change <filename class="directory">/home/foo/perl/lib</filename> to
        your personal Perl library directory. You can probably skip this
        step if you are using the independant method of Perl module
        installation.
      </para>

      <para>When you run <command>./checksetup.pl</command> to create
      the <filename>localconfig</filename> file, it will list the Perl
      modules it finds. If one is missing, go back and double-check the
      module installation from the CPAN shell, then delete the
      <filename>localconfig</filename> file and try again.</para>

      <warning>
        <para>The one option in <filename>localconfig</filename> you
        might have problems with is the web server group. If you can't
        successfully browse to the <filename>index.cgi</filename> (like
        a Forbidden error), you may have to relax your permissions,
        and blank out the web server group. Of course, this may pose
        as a security risk. Having a properly jailed shell and/or
        limited access to shell accounts may lessen the security risk,
        but use at your own risk.</para>
      </warning>

      <section id="suexec">
        <title>suexec or shared hosting</title>

        <para>If you are running on a system that uses suexec (most shared
        hosting environments do this), you will need to set the
        <emphasis>webservergroup</emphasis> value in <filename>localconfig</filename>
        to match <emphasis>your</emphasis> primary group, rather than the one
        the web server runs under.  You will need to run the following
        shell commands after running <command>./checksetup.pl</command>,
        every time you run it (or modify <filename>checksetup.pl</filename>
        to do them for you via the system() command).
        <programlisting>        for i in docs graphs images js skins; do find $i -type d -exec chmod o+rx {} \; ; done
        for i in jpg gif css js png html rdf xul; do find . -name \*.$i -exec chmod o+r {} \; ; done
        find . -name .htaccess -exec chmod o+r {} \;</programlisting>
        Pay particular attention to the number of semicolons and dots.
        They are all important.  A future version of Bugzilla will
        hopefully be able to do this for you out of the box.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

</chapter>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: sgml
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-auto-insert-required-elements:t
sgml-balanced-tag-edit:t
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-general-insert-case:lower
sgml-indent-data:t
sgml-indent-step:2
sgml-local-catalogs:nil
sgml-local-ecat-files:nil
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-namecase-general:t
sgml-omittag:t
sgml-parent-document:("Bugzilla-Guide.xml" "book" "chapter")
sgml-shorttag:t
sgml-tag-region-if-active:t
End:
-->
