<!-- <!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook V4.1//EN" > -->
<!-- Keep these tools listings in alphabetical order please. -MPB -->
<section id="integration">
  <title>Integrating Bugzilla with Third-Party Tools</title>

  <section id="bonsai"
  xreflabel="Bonsai, the Mozilla automated CVS management system">
    <title>Bonsai</title>

    <para>Bonsai is a web-based tool for managing 
    <xref linkend="cvs" />

    . Using Bonsai, administrators can control open/closed status of trees,
    query a fast relational database back-end for change, branch, and comment
    information, and view changes made since the last time the tree was
    closed. Bonsai
    also integrates with  
    <xref linkend="tinderbox" />.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="cvs" xreflabel="CVS, the Concurrent Versioning System">
    <title>CVS</title>

    <para>CVS integration is best accomplished, at this point, using the
    Bugzilla Email Gateway.</para>

    <para>Follow the instructions in this Guide for enabling Bugzilla e-mail
    integration. Ensure that your check-in script sends an email to your
    Bugzilla e-mail gateway with the subject of 
    <quote>[Bug XXXX]</quote>, 
    and you can have CVS check-in comments append to your Bugzilla bug. If
    you  want to have the bug be closed automatically, you'll have to modify
    the <filename>contrib/bugzilla_email_append.pl</filename> script.
    </para>

    <para>There is also a CVSZilla project, based upon somewhat dated 
    Bugzilla code, to integrate CVS and Bugzilla through CVS' ability to 
    email. Check it out at: <ulink url="http://homepages.kcbbs.gen.nz/~tonyg/"/>.
    </para>

    <para>Another system capable of CVS integration with Bugzilla is
    Scmbug. This system provides generic integration of Source code
    Configuration Management with Bugtracking. Check it out at: <ulink
    url="http://freshmeat.net/projects/scmbug/"/>.
    </para>

  </section>

  <section id="scm"
  xreflabel="Perforce SCM (Fast Software Configuration Management System, a powerful commercial alternative to CVS">

    <title>Perforce SCM</title>

    <para>You can find the project page for Bugzilla and Teamtrack Perforce
    integration (p4dti) at: 
    <ulink url="http://www.ravenbrook.com/project/p4dti/"/>

    . 
    <quote>p4dti</quote>

    is now an officially supported product from Perforce, and you can find
    the "Perforce Public Depot" p4dti page at 
    <ulink url="http://public.perforce.com/public/perforce/p4dti/index.html"/>

    .</para>

    <para>Integration of Perforce with Bugzilla, once patches are applied, is
    seamless. Perforce replication information will appear below the comments
    of each bug. Be certain you have a matching set of patches for the
    Bugzilla version you are installing. p4dti is designed to support
    multiple defect trackers, and maintains its own documentation for it.
    Please consult the pages linked above for further information.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="svn"
  xreflabel="Subversion, a compelling replacement for CVS">
     <title>Subversion</title>
     <para>Subversion is a free/open-source version control system,
     designed to overcome various limitations of CVS. Integration of
     Subversion with Bugzilla is possible using Scmbug, a system
     providing generic integration of Source Code Configuration
     Management with Bugtracking. Scmbug is available at <ulink
     url="http://freshmeat.net/projects/scmbug/"/>.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="tinderbox"
  xreflabel="Tinderbox, the Mozilla automated build management system">
    <title>Tinderbox/Tinderbox2</title>

    <para>Tinderbox is a continuous-build system which can integrate with
    Bugzilla - see
    <ulink url="http://www.mozilla.org/projects/tinderbox"/> for details
    of Tinderbox, and 
    <ulink url="http://tinderbox.mozilla.org/showbuilds.cgi"/> to see it
    in action.</para>
  </section>
</section>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: sgml
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-auto-insert-required-elements:t
sgml-balanced-tag-edit:t
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-general-insert-case:lower
sgml-indent-data:t
sgml-indent-step:2
sgml-local-catalogs:nil
sgml-local-ecat-files:nil
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-namecase-general:t
sgml-omittag:t
sgml-parent-document:("Bugzilla-Guide.xml" "book" "chapter")
sgml-shorttag:t
sgml-tag-region-if-active:t
End:
-->

