<!-- <!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook V4.1//EN"> -->

<chapter id="using">
  <title>Using Bugzilla</title>

  <section id="using-intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>This section contains information for end-users of Bugzilla.  There
    is a Bugzilla test installation, called
    <ulink url="http://landfill.bugzilla.org/">Landfill</ulink>, which you are
    welcome to play with (if it's up). However, not all of the Bugzilla
    installations there will necessarily have all Bugzilla features enabled,
    and different installations run different versions, so some things may not
    quite work as this document describes.</para>

    <para>
      Frequently Asked Questions (FAQ) are available and answered on
      <ulink url="http://wiki.mozilla.org/Bugzilla:FAQ">wiki.mozilla.org</ulink>.
      They may cover some questions you have which are left unanswered.
    </para>
  </section>
      
  <section id="myaccount">
    <title>Create a Bugzilla Account</title>

    <para>If you want to use Bugzilla, first you need to create an account.
    Consult with the administrator responsible for your installation of
    Bugzilla for the URL you should use to access it. If you're
    test-driving Bugzilla, use this URL: 
    <ulink url="&landfillbase;"/>.
    </para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          On the home page <filename>index.cgi</filename>, click the
          <quote>Open a new Bugzilla account</quote> link, or the
          <quote>New Account</quote> link available in the footer of pages.
          Now enter your email address, then click the <quote>Send</quote>
          button.
        </para>

        <note>
          <para>
            If none of these links is available, this means that the
            administrator of the installation has disabled self-registration.
            This means that only an administrator can create accounts
            for other users. One reason could be that this installation is
            private.
          </para>
        </note>

        <note>
          <para>
            Also, if only some users are allowed to create an account on
            the installation, you may see these links but your registration
            may fail if your email address doesn't match the ones accepted
            by the installation. This is another way to restrict who can
            access and edit bugs in this installation.
          </para>
        </note>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Within moments, and if your registration is accepted, you should
          receive an email to the address you provided, which contains your
          login name (generally the same as the email address), and two URLs
          with a token (a random string generated by the installation) to
          confirm, respectively cancel, your registration. This is a way to
          prevent users from abusing the generation of user accounts, for
          instance by entering inexistent email addresses, or email addresses
          which do not belong to them.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          By default, you have 3 days to confirm your registration. Past this
          timeframe, the token is invalidated and the registration is
          automatically canceled. You can also cancel this registration sooner
          by using the appropriate URL in the email you got.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          If you confirm your registration, Bugzilla will ask you your real name
          (optional, but recommended) and your password, which must be between
          3 and 16 characters long.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Now all you need to do is to click the <quote>Log In</quote>
          link in the footer at the bottom of the page in your browser,
          enter your email address and password you just chose into the
          login form, and click the <quote>Log in</quote> button.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>
      You are now logged in. Bugzilla uses cookies to remember you are
      logged in so, unless you have cookies disabled or your IP address changes,
      you should not have to log in again during your session.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="bug_page">
    <title>Anatomy of a Bug</title>

    <para>The core of Bugzilla is the screen which displays a particular
    bug. It's a good place to explain some Bugzilla concepts. 
    <ulink
    url="&landfillbase;show_bug.cgi?id=1">
    Bug 1 on Landfill</ulink>

    is a good example. Note that the labels for most fields are hyperlinks;
    clicking them will take you to context-sensitive help on that
    particular field. Fields marked * may not be present on every
    installation of Bugzilla.</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        <emphasis>Product and Component</emphasis>: 
        Bugs are divided up by Product and Component, with a Product
        having one or more Components in it. For example,
        bugzilla.mozilla.org's "Bugzilla" Product is composed of several
        Components: 
        <simplelist>
        <member>
        <emphasis>Administration:</emphasis>
        Administration of a Bugzilla installation.</member>

        <member>
        <emphasis>Bugzilla-General:</emphasis>
        Anything that doesn't fit in the other components, or spans
        multiple components.</member>

        <member>
        <emphasis>Creating/Changing Bugs:</emphasis>
        Creating, changing, and viewing bugs.</member>

        <member>
        <emphasis>Documentation:</emphasis>
        The Bugzilla documentation, including The Bugzilla Guide.</member>

        <member>
        <emphasis>Email:</emphasis>
        Anything to do with email sent by Bugzilla.</member>

        <member>
        <emphasis>Installation:</emphasis>
        The installation process of Bugzilla.</member>

        <member>
        <emphasis>Query/Buglist:</emphasis>
        Anything to do with searching for bugs and viewing the
        buglists.</member>

        <member>
        <emphasis>Reporting/Charting:</emphasis>
        Getting reports from Bugzilla.</member>

        <member>
        <emphasis>User Accounts:</emphasis>
        Anything about managing a user account from the user's perspective.
        Saved queries, creating accounts, changing passwords, logging in,
        etc.</member>

        <member>
        <emphasis>User Interface:</emphasis>
        General issues having to do with the user interface cosmetics (not
        functionality) including cosmetic issues, HTML templates,
        etc.</member>
        </simplelist>
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
        <emphasis>Status and Resolution:</emphasis>

        These define exactly what state the bug is in - from not even
        being confirmed as a bug, through to being fixed and the fix
        confirmed by Quality Assurance. The different possible values for
        Status and Resolution on your installation should be documented in the
        context-sensitive help for those items.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
        <emphasis>Assigned To:</emphasis>
        The person responsible for fixing the bug.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
        <emphasis>*QA Contact:</emphasis>
        The person responsible for quality assurance on this bug.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
        <emphasis>*URL:</emphasis>
        A URL associated with the bug, if any.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
        <emphasis>Summary:</emphasis>
        A one-sentence summary of the problem.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
        <emphasis>*Status Whiteboard:</emphasis>
        (a.k.a. Whiteboard) A free-form text area for adding short notes
        and tags to a bug.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
        <emphasis>*Keywords:</emphasis>
        The administrator can define keywords which you can use to tag and
        categorise bugs - e.g. The Mozilla Project has keywords like crash
        and regression.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
        <emphasis>Platform and OS:</emphasis>
        These indicate the computing environment where the bug was
        found.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
        <emphasis>Version:</emphasis>
        The "Version" field is usually used for versions of a product which
        have been released, and is set to indicate which versions of a
        Component have the particular problem the bug report is
        about.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
        <emphasis>Priority:</emphasis>
        The bug assignee uses this field to prioritize his or her bugs.
        It's a good idea not to change this on other people's bugs.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
        <emphasis>Severity:</emphasis>
        This indicates how severe the problem is - from blocker
        ("application unusable") to trivial ("minor cosmetic issue"). You
        can also use this field to indicate whether a bug is an enhancement
        request.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
        <emphasis>*Target:</emphasis>
        (a.k.a. Target Milestone) A future version by which the bug is to
        be fixed. e.g. The Bugzilla Project's milestones for future
        Bugzilla versions are 2.18, 2.20, 3.0, etc. Milestones are not
        restricted to numbers, thought - you can use any text strings, such
        as dates.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
        <emphasis>Reporter:</emphasis>
        The person who filed the bug.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
        <emphasis>CC list:</emphasis>
        A list of people who get mail when the bug changes.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
        <emphasis>*Time Tracking:</emphasis>
        This form can be used for time tracking.
        To use this feature, you have to be blessed group membership
        specified by the <quote>timetrackinggroup</quote> parameter.
        <simplelist>
        <member>
        <emphasis>Orig. Est.:</emphasis>
        This field shows the original estimated time.</member>

        <member>
        <emphasis>Current Est.:</emphasis>
        This field shows the current estimated time.
        This number is calculated from <quote>Hours Worked</quote>
        and <quote>Hours Left</quote>.</member>

        <member>
        <emphasis>Hours Worked:</emphasis>
        This field shows the number of hours worked.</member>

        <member>
        <emphasis>Hours Left:</emphasis>
        This field shows the <quote>Current Est.</quote> -
        <quote>Hours Worked</quote>.
        This value + <quote>Hours Worked</quote> will become the
        new Current Est.</member>

        <member>
        <emphasis>%Complete:</emphasis>
        This field shows what percentage of the task is complete.</member>

        <member>
        <emphasis>Gain:</emphasis>
        This field shows the number of hours that the bug is ahead of the
        <quote>Orig. Est.</quote>.</member>

        <member>
        <emphasis>Deadline:</emphasis>
        This field shows the deadline for this bug.</member>
        </simplelist>
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
        <emphasis>Attachments:</emphasis>
          You can attach files (e.g. testcases or patches) to bugs. If there
          are any attachments, they are listed in this section.  Attachments are
          normally stored in the Bugzilla database, unless they are marked as
          Big Files, which are stored directly on disk.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
        <emphasis>*Dependencies:</emphasis>
        If this bug cannot be fixed unless other bugs are fixed (depends
        on), or this bug stops other bugs being fixed (blocks), their
        numbers are recorded here.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
        <emphasis>*Votes:</emphasis>
        Whether this bug has any votes.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
        <emphasis>Additional Comments:</emphasis>
        You can add your two cents to the bug discussion here, if you have
        something worthwhile to say.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="lifecycle">
    <title>Life Cycle of a Bug</title>

    <para>
      The life cycle, also known as work flow, of a bug is currently hardcoded
      into Bugzilla. <xref linkend="lifecycle-image"/> contains a graphical
      representation of this life cycle. If you wish to customize this image for
      your site, the <ulink url="../images/bzLifecycle.xml">diagram file</ulink>
      is available in <ulink url="http://www.gnome.org/projects/dia">Dia's</ulink>
      native XML format.
    </para>

    <figure id="lifecycle-image">
      <title>Lifecycle of a Bugzilla Bug</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/bzLifecycle.png" scale="66" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section id="query">
    <title>Searching for Bugs</title>

    <para>The Bugzilla Search page is the interface where you can find
    any bug report, comment, or patch currently in the Bugzilla system. You
    can play with it here: 
    <ulink url="&landfillbase;query.cgi"/>.</para>

    <para>The Search page has controls for selecting different possible
    values for all of the fields in a bug, as described above. For some
    fields, multiple values can be selected. In those cases, Bugzilla
    returns bugs where the content of the field matches any one of the selected
    values. If none is selected, then the field can take any value.</para>

    <para>
      After a search is run, you can save it as a Saved Search, which
      will appear in the page footer. If you are in the group defined 
      by the "querysharegroup" parameter, you may share your queries 
      with other users, see <xref linkend="savedsearches"/> for more details.
    </para>

    <section id="boolean">
      <title>Boolean Charts</title>
      <para>
        Highly advanced querying is done using Boolean Charts.
      </para>
      <para>
        The boolean charts further restrict the set of results
        returned by a query. It is possible to search for bugs
        based on elaborate combinations of criteria.
      </para>
      <para>
        The simplest boolean searches have only one term. These searches
        permit the selected left <emphasis>field</emphasis>
        to be compared using a
        selectable <emphasis>operator</emphasis> to a
        specified <emphasis>value.</emphasis>
        Using the "And," "Or," and "Add Another Boolean Chart" buttons, 
        additional terms can be included in the query, further
        altering the list of bugs returned by the query.
      </para>
      <para>
        There are three fields in each row of a boolean search. 
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Field:</emphasis>
            the items being searched 
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Operator:</emphasis>
            the comparison operator 
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Value:</emphasis>
            the value to which the field is being compared
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <section id="pronouns">
        <title>Pronoun Substitution</title>
        <para>
          Sometimes, a query needs to compare a user-related field
          (such as ReportedBy) with a role-specific user (such as the
          user running the query or the user to whom each bug is assigned).
          When the operator is either "equals" or "notequals", the value
          can be "%reporter%", "%assignee%", "%qacontact%", or "%user%".
          The user pronoun
          refers to the user who is executing the query or, in the case
          of whining reports, the user who will be the recipient
          of the report. The reporter, assignee, and qacontact
          pronouns refer to the corresponding fields in the bug.
        </para>
        <para>
          Boolean charts also let you type a group name in any user-related
          field if the operator is either "equals", "notequals" or "anyexact".
          This will let you query for any member belonging (or not) to the
          specified group. The group name must be entered following the
          "%group.foo%" syntax, where "foo" is the group name.
          So if you are looking for bugs reported by any user being in the
          "editbugs" group, then you can type "%group.editbugs%".
        </para>
      </section>
      <section id="negation">
        <title>Negation</title>
        <para>
          At first glance, negation seems redundant. Rather than
          searching for
          <blockquote>
            <para>
              NOT("summary" "contains the string" "foo"),
            </para>
          </blockquote>
          one could search for 
          <blockquote>
            <para>
              ("summary" "does not contain the string" "foo").
            </para>
          </blockquote>
          However, the search 
          <blockquote>
            <para>
              ("CC" "does not contain the string" "@mozilla.org")
            </para>
          </blockquote>
          would find every bug where anyone on the CC list did not contain 
          "@mozilla.org" while
          <blockquote>
            <para>
              NOT("CC" "contains the string" "@mozilla.org")
            </para>
          </blockquote>
          would find every bug where there was nobody on the CC list who
          did contain the string. Similarly, the use of negation also permits
          complex expressions to be built using terms OR'd together and then
          negated. Negation permits queries such as
          <blockquote>
            <para>
              NOT(("product" "equals" "update") OR 
            ("component" "equals" "Documentation"))
            </para>
          </blockquote>
          to find bugs that are neither 
          in the update product or in the documentation component or
          <blockquote>
            <para>
              NOT(("commenter" "equals" "%assignee%") OR 
              ("component" "equals" "Documentation"))
            </para>
          </blockquote>
          to find non-documentation
          bugs on which the assignee has never commented.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section id="multiplecharts">
        <title>Multiple Charts</title>
        <para>
          The terms within a single row of a boolean chart are all
          constraints on a single piece of data. If you are looking for
          a bug that has two different people cc'd on it, then you need 
          to use two boolean charts. A search for
          <blockquote>
            <para>
              ("cc" "contains the string" "foo@") AND
              ("cc" "contains the string" "@mozilla.org")
            </para>
          </blockquote>
          would return only bugs with "foo@mozilla.org" on the cc list.
          If you wanted bugs where there is someone on the cc list
          containing "foo@" and someone else containing "@mozilla.org",
          then you would need two boolean charts.
          <blockquote>
            <para>
              First chart: ("cc" "contains the string" "foo@")
            </para>
            <para>
              Second chart: ("cc" "contains the string" "@mozilla.org")
            </para>
          </blockquote>
          The bugs listed will be only the bugs where ALL the charts are true.
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="quicksearch">
      <title>Quicksearch</title>

      <para>
        Quicksearch is a single-text-box query tool which uses
        metacharacters to indicate what is to be searched. For example, typing
        "<literal>foo|bar</literal>"
        into Quicksearch would search for "foo" or "bar" in the
        summary and status whiteboard of a bug; adding
        "<literal>:BazProduct</literal>" would
        search only in that product.
        You can use it to find a bug by its number or its alias, too.
      </para>

      <para>
        You'll find the Quicksearch box in Bugzilla's footer area.
        On Bugzilla's front page, there is an additional
        <ulink url="../../page.cgi?id=quicksearch.html">Help</ulink>
        link which details how to use it.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="casesensitivity">
      <title>Case Sensitivity in Searches</title>
      <para>
      Bugzilla queries are case-insensitive and accent-insensitive, when
      used with either MySQL or Oracle databases. When using Bugzilla with
      PostgreSQL, however, some queries are case-sensitive. This is due to
      the way PostgreSQL handles case and accent sensitivity. 
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="list">
      <title>Bug Lists</title>

      <para>If you run a search, a list of matching bugs will be returned.
      </para>

      <para>The format of the list is configurable. For example, it can be
      sorted by clicking the column headings. Other useful features can be
      accessed using the links at the bottom of the list:
      <simplelist>
        <member>
        <emphasis>Long Format:</emphasis>

        this gives you a large page with a non-editable summary of the fields
        of each bug.</member>

        <member>
        <emphasis>XML:</emphasis>

        get the buglist in the XML format.</member>

        <member>
        <emphasis>CSV:</emphasis>

        get the buglist as comma-separated values, for import into e.g.
        a spreadsheet.</member>

        <member>
        <emphasis>Feed:</emphasis>

        get the buglist as an Atom feed.  Copy this link into your
        favorite feed reader.  If you are using Firefox, you can also
        save the list as a live bookmark by clicking the live bookmark
        icon in the status bar.  To limit the number of bugs in the feed,
        add a limit=n parameter to the URL.</member>

        <member>
        <emphasis>iCalendar:</emphasis>

        Get the buglist as an iCalendar file. Each bug is represented as a
        to-do item in the imported calendar.</member>

        <member>
        <emphasis>Change Columns:</emphasis>

        change the bug attributes which appear in the list.</member>

        <member>
        <emphasis>Change several bugs at once:</emphasis>

        If your account is sufficiently empowered, and more than one bug
        appear in the bug list, this link is displayed which lets you make
        the same change to all the bugs in the list - for example, changing
        their assignee.</member>

        <member>
        <emphasis>Send mail to bug assignees:</emphasis>

        If more than one bug appear in the bug list and there are at least
        two distinct bug assignees, this links is displayed which lets you
        easily send a mail to the assignees of all bugs on the list.</member>

        <member>
        <emphasis>Edit Search:</emphasis>

        If you didn't get exactly the results you were looking for, you can
        return to the Query page through this link and make small revisions
        to the query you just made so you get more accurate results.</member>

        <member>
        <emphasis>Remember Search As:</emphasis>

        You can give a search a name and remember it; a link will appear
        in your page footer giving you quick access to run it again later.
        </member>
      </simplelist>
      </para>

      <para>
        If you would like to access the bug list from another program
        it is often useful to have the list returned in something other
        than HTML. By adding the ctype=type parameter into the bug list URL
        you can specify several alternate formats. Besides the types described
        above, the following formats are also supported: ECMAScript, also known
        as JavaScript (ctype=js), and Resource Description Framework RDF/XML
        (ctype=rdf).
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="individual-buglists">
      <title>Adding/removing tags to/from bugs</title>
      <para>
        You can add and remove tags from individual bugs, which let you find and
        manage them more easily. Creating a new tag automatically generates a saved
        search - whose name is the name of the tag - which lists bugs with this tag.
        This saved search will be displayed in the footer of pages by default, as
        all other saved searches. The main difference between tags and normal saved
        searches is that saved searches, as described in the previous section, are
        stored in the form of a list of matching criteria, while the saved search
        generated by tags is a list of bug numbers. Consequently, you can easily
        edit this list by either adding or removing tags from bugs. To enable this
        feature, you have to turn on the <quote>Enable tags for bugs</quote> user
        preference, see <xref linkend="userpreferences" />. This feature is disabled
        by default.
      </para>

      <para>
        This feature is useful when you want to keep track of several bugs, but
        for different reasons. Instead of adding yourself to the CC list of all
        these bugs and mixing all these reasons, you can now store these bugs in
        separate lists, e.g. <quote>Keep in mind</quote>, <quote>Interesting bugs</quote>,
        or <quote>Triage</quote>. One big advantage of this way to manage bugs
        is that you can easily add or remove bugs one by one, which is not
        possible to do with saved searches without having to edit the search
        criteria again.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="bugreports">
    <title>Filing Bugs</title>

    <section id="fillingbugs">
      <title>Reporting a New Bug</title>
    
      <para>Years of bug writing experience has been distilled for your
      reading pleasure into the 
      <ulink
      url="&landfillbase;page.cgi?id=bug-writing.html">
      Bug Writing Guidelines</ulink>. 
      While some of the advice is Mozilla-specific, the basic principles of
      reporting Reproducible, Specific bugs, isolating the Product you are
      using, the Version of the Product, the Component which failed, the
      Hardware Platform, and Operating System you were using at the time of
      the failure go a long way toward ensuring accurate, responsible fixes
      for the bug that bit you.</para>

      <para>The procedure for filing a bug is as follows:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Click the <quote>New</quote> link available in the footer
            of pages, or the <quote>Enter a new bug report</quote> link
            displayed on the home page of the Bugzilla installation.
          </para>

          <note>
            <para>
              If you want to file a test bug to see how Bugzilla works,
              you can do it on one of our test installations on
              <ulink url="&landfillbase;">Landfill</ulink>.
            </para>
          </note>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            You first have to select the product in which you found a bug.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            You now see a form where you can specify the component (part of
            the product which is affected by the bug you discovered; if you have
            no idea, just select <quote>General</quote> if such a component exists),
            the version of the program you were using, the Operating System and
            platform your program is running on and the severity of the bug (if the
            bug you found crashes the program, it's probably a major or a critical
            bug; if it's a typo somewhere, that's something pretty minor; if it's
            something you would like to see implemented, then that's an enhancement).
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            You now have to give a short but descriptive summary of the bug you found.
            <quote>My program is crashing all the time</quote> is a very poor summary
            and doesn't help developers at all. Try something more meaningful or
            your bug will probably be ignored due to a lack of precision.
            The next step is to give a very detailed list of steps to reproduce
            the problem you encountered. Try to limit these steps to a minimum set
            required to reproduce the problem. This will make the life of
            developers easier, and the probability that they consider your bug in
            a reasonable timeframe will be much higher.
          </para>

          <note>
            <para>
              Try to make sure that everything in the summary is also in the first
              comment. Summaries are often updated and this will ensure your original
              information is easily accessible.
            </para>
          </note>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            As you file the bug, you can also attach a document (testcase, patch,
            or screenshot of the problem).
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Depending on the Bugzilla installation you are using and the product in
            which you are filing the bug, you can also request developers to consider
            your bug in different ways (such as requesting review for the patch you
            just attached, requesting your bug to block the next release of the
            product, and many other product specific requests).
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Now is a good time to read your bug report again. Remove all misspellings,
            otherwise your bug may not be found by developers running queries for some
            specific words, and so your bug would not get any attention.
            Also make sure you didn't forget any important information developers
            should know in order to reproduce the problem, and make sure your
            description of the problem is explicit and clear enough.
            When you think your bug report is ready to go, the last step is to
            click the <quote>Commit</quote> button to add your report into the database.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>
      You do not need to put "any" or similar strings in the URL field.
      If there is no specific URL associated with the bug, leave this 
      field blank.
      </para> 

      <para>If you feel a bug you filed was incorrectly marked as a
      DUPLICATE of another, please question it in your bug, not      
      the bug it was duped to. Feel free to CC the person who duped it 
      if they are not already CCed.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="cloningbugs">
      <title>Clone an Existing Bug</title>

      <para>
        Starting with version 2.20, Bugzilla has a feature that allows you
        to clone an existing bug. The newly created bug will inherit
        most settings from the old bug. This allows you to track more
        easily similar concerns in a new bug. To use this, go to the bug
        that you want to clone, then click the <quote>Clone This Bug</quote>
        link on the bug page. This will take you to the <quote>Enter Bug</quote>
        page that is filled with the values that the old bug has.
        You can change those values and/or texts if needed.
      </para>
    </section>
      
  </section>

  <section id="attachments">
    <title>Attachments</title>

    <para>
      You should use attachments, rather than comments, for large chunks of ASCII
      data, such as trace, debugging output files, or log files. That way, it
      doesn't bloat the bug for everyone who wants to read it, and cause people to
      receive fat, useless mails.
    </para>

    <para>You should make sure to trim screenshots. There's no need to show the
      whole screen if you are pointing out a single-pixel problem.
    </para>

    <para>Bugzilla stores and uses a Content-Type for each attachment
      (e.g. text/html). To download an attachment as a different
      Content-Type (e.g. application/xhtml+xml), you can override this
      using a 'content_type' parameter on the URL, e.g.
      <filename>&amp;content_type=text/plain</filename>.
    </para>

    <para>
      If you have a really large attachment, something that does not need to
      be recorded forever (as most attachments are), or something that is too
      big for your database, you can mark your attachment as a
      <quote>Big File</quote>, assuming the administrator of the installation
      has enabled this feature.  Big Files are stored directly on disk instead
      of in the database.  The maximum size of a <quote>Big File</quote> is
      normally larger than the maximum size of a regular attachment. Independently
      of the storage system used, an administrator can delete these attachments
      at any time. Nevertheless, if these files are stored in the database, the
      <quote>allow_attachment_deletion</quote> parameter (which is turned off
      by default) must be enabled in order to delete them.
    </para>

    <para>
      Also, if the administrator turned on the <quote>allow_attach_url</quote>
      parameter, you can enter the URL pointing to the attachment instead of
      uploading the attachment itself. For example, this is useful if you want to
      point to an external application, a website or a very large file. Note that
      there is no guarantee that the source file will always be available, nor
      that its content will remain unchanged.
    </para>

    <section id="patchviewer">
      <title>Patch Viewer</title>

      <para>Viewing and reviewing patches in Bugzilla is often difficult due to
      lack of context, improper format and the inherent readability issues that
      raw patches present.  Patch Viewer is an enhancement to Bugzilla designed
      to fix that by offering increased context, linking to sections, and
      integrating with Bonsai, LXR and CVS.</para>

      <para>Patch viewer allows you to:</para>

      <simplelist>
        <member>View patches in color, with side-by-side view rather than trying
        to interpret the contents of the patch.</member>
        <member>See the difference between two patches.</member>
        <member>Get more context in a patch.</member>
        <member>Collapse and expand sections of a patch for easy
        reading.</member>
        <member>Link to a particular section of a patch for discussion or
        review</member>
        <member>Go to Bonsai or LXR to see more context, blame, and
        cross-references for the part of the patch you are looking at</member>
        <member>Create a rawtext unified format diff out of any patch, no
        matter what format it came from</member>
      </simplelist>

      <section id="patchviewer_view">
        <title>Viewing Patches in Patch Viewer</title>
        <para>The main way to view a patch in patch viewer is to click on the
        "Diff" link next to a patch in the Attachments list on a bug. You may
        also do this within the edit window by clicking the "View Attachment As
        Diff" button in the Edit Attachment screen.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="patchviewer_diff">
        <title>Seeing the Difference Between Two Patches</title>
        <para>To see the difference between two patches, you must first view the
        newer patch in Patch Viewer.  Then select the older patch from the
        dropdown at the top of the page ("Differences between [dropdown] and
        this patch") and click the "Diff" button. This will show you what
        is new or changed in the newer patch.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="patchviewer_context">
        <title>Getting More Context in a Patch</title>
        <para>To get more context in a patch, you put a number in the textbox at
        the top of Patch Viewer ("Patch / File / [textbox]") and hit enter.
        This will give you that many lines of context before and after each
        change. Alternatively, you can click on the "File" link there and it
        will show each change in the full context of the file. This feature only
        works against files that were diffed using "cvs diff".</para>
      </section>

      <section id="patchviewer_collapse">
        <title>Collapsing and Expanding Sections of a Patch</title>
        <para>To view only a certain set of files in a patch (for example, if a
        patch is absolutely huge and you want to only review part of it at a
        time), you can click the "(+)" and "(-)" links next to each file (to
        expand it or collapse it). If you want to collapse all files or expand
        all files, you can click the "Collapse All" and "Expand All" links at the
        top of the page.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="patchviewer_link">
        <title>Linking to a Section of a Patch</title>
        <para>To link to a section of a patch (for example, if you want to be
        able to give someone a URL to show them which part you are talking
        about) you simply click the "Link Here" link on the section header. The
        resulting URL can be copied and used in discussion.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="patchviewer_bonsai_lxr">
        <title>Going to Bonsai and LXR</title>
        <para>To go to Bonsai to get blame for the lines you are interested in,
        you can click the "Lines XX-YY" link on the section header you are
        interested in. This works even if the patch is against an old
        version of the file, since Bonsai stores all versions of the file.</para>

        <para>To go to LXR, you click on the filename on the file header
        (unfortunately, since LXR only does the most recent version, line
        numbers are likely to rot).</para>
      </section>

      <section id="patchviewer_unified_diff">
        <title>Creating a Unified Diff</title>
        <para>If the patch is not in a format that you like, you can turn it
        into a unified diff format by clicking the "Raw Unified" link at the top
        of the page.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="hintsandtips">
    <title>Hints and Tips</title>

    <para>This section distills some Bugzilla tips and best practices
    that have been developed.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Autolinkification</title>
      <para>Bugzilla comments are plain text - so typing &lt;U&gt; will
      produce less-than, U, greater-than rather than underlined text.
      However, Bugzilla will automatically make hyperlinks out of certain
      sorts of text in comments. For example, the text 
      "http://www.bugzilla.org" will be turned into a link:
      <ulink url="http://www.bugzilla.org"/>.
      Other strings which get linkified in the obvious manner are:
      <simplelist>
        <member>bug 12345</member>
        <member>comment 7</member>
        <member>bug 23456, comment 53</member>
        <member>attachment 4321</member>
        <member>mailto:george@example.com</member>
        <member>george@example.com</member>
        <member>ftp://ftp.mozilla.org</member>
        <member>Most other sorts of URL</member>
      </simplelist>
      </para>

      <para>A corollary here is that if you type a bug number in a comment,
      you should put the word "bug" before it, so it gets autolinkified
      for the convenience of others.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="commenting">
      <title>Comments</title>

      <para>If you are changing the fields on a bug, only comment if
      either you have something pertinent to say, or Bugzilla requires it.
      Otherwise, you may spam people unnecessarily with bug mail.
      To take an example: a user can set up their account to filter out messages
      where someone just adds themselves to the CC field of a bug
      (which happens a lot.) If you come along, add yourself to the CC field,
      and add a comment saying "Adding self to CC", then that person
      gets a pointless piece of mail they would otherwise have avoided.
      </para>

      <para>
      Don't use sigs in comments. Signing your name ("Bill") is acceptable,
      if you do it out of habit, but full mail/news-style
      four line ASCII art creations are not.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="comment-wrapping">
      <title>Server-Side Comment Wrapping</title>
      <para>
      Bugzilla stores comments unwrapped and wraps them at display time. This
      ensures proper wrapping in all browsers. Lines beginning with the ">" 
      character are assumed to be quotes, and are not wrapped.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="dependencytree">
      <title>Dependency Tree</title>

      <para>
        On the <quote>Dependency tree</quote> page linked from each bug
        page, you can see the dependency relationship from the bug as a
        tree structure.
      </para>

      <para>
        You can change how much depth to show, and you can hide resolved bugs
        from this page. You can also collaps/expand dependencies for
        each bug on the tree view, using the [-]/[+] buttons that appear
        before its summary. This option is not available for terminal
        bugs in the tree (that don't have further dependencies).
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="timetracking">
    <title>Time Tracking Information</title>

    <para>
      Users who belong to the group specified by the <quote>timetrackinggroup</quote>
      parameter have access to time-related fields. Developers can see
      deadlines and estimated times to fix bugs, and can provide time spent
      on these bugs.
    </para>

    <para>
      At any time, a summary of the time spent by developers on bugs is
      accessible either from bug lists when clicking the <quote>Time Summary</quote>
      button or from individual bugs when clicking the <quote>Summarize time</quote>
      link in the time tracking table. The <filename>summarize_time.cgi</filename>
      page lets you view this information either per developer or per bug,
      and can be split on a month basis to have greater details on how time
      is spent by developers.
    </para>

    <para>
      As soon as a bug is marked as RESOLVED, the remaining time expected
      to fix the bug is set to zero. This lets QA people set it again for
      their own usage, and it will be set to zero again when the bug will
      be marked as CLOSED.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="userpreferences">
    <title>User Preferences</title>

    <para>
    Once logged in, you can customize various aspects of
    Bugzilla via the "Preferences" link in the page footer.
    The preferences are split into five tabs:</para>

    <section id="generalpreferences" xreflabel="General Preferences">
      <title>General Preferences</title>

      <para>
        This tab allows you to change several default settings of Bugzilla.
      </para>

      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Bugzilla's general appearance (skin) - select which skin to use.
            Bugzilla supports adding custom skins.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Quote the associated comment when you click on its reply link - sets
            the behavior of the comment "Reply" link. Options include quoting the
            full comment, just reference the comment number, or turn the link off.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Language used in email - select which language email will be sent in,
            from the list of available languages.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            After changing a bug - This controls what page is displayed after
            changes to a bug are submitted. The options include to show the bug
            just modified, to show the next bug in your list, or to do nothing.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Enable tags for bugs - turn bug tagging on or off.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Zoom textareas large when in use (requires JavaScript) - enable or
            disable the automatic expanding of text areas when  text is being
            entered into them. 
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Field separator character for CSV files -
            Select between a comma and semi-colon for exported CSV bug lists.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Automatically add me to the CC list of bugs I change - set default
            behavior of CC list. Options include "Always", "Never", and "Only
            if I have no role on them". 
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When viewing a bug, show comments in this order -
            controls the order of comments. Options include "Oldest
            to Newest", "Newest to Oldest" and "Newest to Oldest, but keep the
            bug description at the top".
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Show a quip at the top of each bug list - controls
            whether a quip will be shown on the Bug list page.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="emailpreferences">
      <title>Email Preferences</title>

      <para>
        This tab allows you to enable or disable email notification on
        specific events.
      </para>

      <para>
        In general, users have almost complete control over how much (or
        how little) email Bugzilla sends them. If you want to receive the
        maximum amount of email possible, click the <quote>Enable All 
        Mail</quote> button. If you don't want to receive any email from
        Bugzilla at all, click the <quote>Disable All Mail</quote> button.
      </para>

      <note>
        <para>
          A Bugzilla administrator can stop a user from receiving
          bugmail by clicking the <quote>Bugmail Disabled</quote> checkbox
          when editing the user account. This is a drastic step
          best taken only for disabled accounts, as it overrides 
          the user's individual mail preferences.
        </para>
      </note>
  
      <para>
        There are two global options -- <quote>Email me when someone
        asks me to set a flag</quote> and <quote>Email me when someone
        sets a flag I asked for</quote>. These define how you want to
        receive bugmail with regards to flags. Their use is quite
        straightforward; enable the checkboxes if you want Bugzilla to
        send you mail under either of the above conditions.
      </para>

      <para>
        If you'd like to set your bugmail to something besides
        'Completely ON' and 'Completely OFF', the
        <quote>Field/recipient specific options</quote> table
        allows you to do just that. The rows of the table
        define events that can happen to a bug -- things like
        attachments being added, new comments being made, the
        priority changing, etc. The columns in the table define
        your relationship with the bug:
      </para>

      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Reporter - Where you are the person who initially
            reported the bug. Your name/account appears in the
            <quote>Reporter:</quote> field.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Assignee - Where you are the person who has been
            designated as the one responsible for the bug. Your
            name/account appears in the <quote>Assigned To:</quote>
            field of the bug.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            QA Contact - You are one of the designated
            QA Contacts for the bug. Your account appears in the 
            <quote>QA Contact:</quote> text-box of the bug.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            CC - You are on the list CC List for the bug.
            Your account appears in the <quote>CC:</quote> text box
            of the bug.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Voter - You have placed one or more votes for the bug.
            Your account appears only if someone clicks on the 
            <quote>Show votes for this bug</quote> link on the bug.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <note>
        <para>
          Some columns may not be visible for your installation, depending
          on your site's configuration.
        </para>
      </note>

      <para>
        To fine-tune your bugmail, decide the events for which you want
        to receive bugmail; then decide if you want to receive it all
        the time (enable the checkbox for every column), or only when
        you have a certain relationship with a bug (enable the checkbox
        only for those columns). For example: if you didn't want to
        receive mail when someone added themselves to the CC list, you
        could uncheck all the boxes in the <quote>CC Field Changes</quote>
        line. As another example, if you never wanted to receive email
        on bugs you reported unless the bug was resolved, you would
        un-check all boxes in the <quote>Reporter</quote> column
        except for the one on the <quote>The bug is resolved or
        verified</quote> row.
      </para>

      <note>
        <para>
          Bugzilla adds the <quote>X-Bugzilla-Reason</quote> header to
          all bugmail it sends, describing the recipient's relationship
          (AssignedTo, Reporter, QAContact, CC, or Voter) to the bug.
          This header can be used to do further client-side filtering.
        </para>
      </note>

      <para>
        Bugzilla has a feature called <quote>Users Watching</quote>.
        When you enter one or more comma-delineated user accounts (usually email
        addresses) into the text entry box, you will receive a copy of all the
        bugmail those users are sent (security settings permitting).
        This powerful functionality enables seamless transitions as developers
        change projects or users go on holiday.
      </para>

      <note>
        <para>
          The ability to watch other users may not be available in all
          Bugzilla installations. If you don't see this feature, and feel
          that you need it, speak to your administrator.
        </para>
      </note>

      <para>
        Each user listed in the <quote>Users watching you</quote> field
        has you listed in their <quote>Users to watch</quote> list
        and can get bugmail according to your relationship to the bug and
        their <quote>Field/recipient specific options</quote> setting.
      </para>

    </section>

    <section id="savedsearches" xreflabel="Saved Searches">
      <title>Saved Searches</title>
      <para>
      On this tab you can view and run any Saved Searches that you have
      created, and also any Saved Searches that other members of the group
      defined in the "querysharegroup" parameter have shared. 
      Saved Searches can be added to the page footer from this screen. 
      If somebody is sharing a Search with a group she or he is allowed to
      <link linkend="groups">assign users to</link>, the sharer may opt to have
      the Search show up in the footer of the group's direct members by default.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="accountpreferences" xreflabel="Name and Password">
      <title>Name and Password</title>

      <para>On this tab, you can change your basic account information,
      including your password, email address and real name. For security
      reasons, in order to change anything on this page you must type your
      <emphasis>current</emphasis> password into the <quote>Password</quote>
      field at the top of the page.
      If you attempt to change your email address, a confirmation
      email is sent to both the old and new addresses, with a link to use to
      confirm the change. This helps to prevent account hijacking.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="permissionsettings">
      <title>Permissions</title>
      
      <para>
      This is a purely informative page which outlines your current
      permissions on this installation of Bugzilla.
      </para>

      <para>
      A complete list of permissions is below. Only users with 
      <emphasis>editusers</emphasis> privileges can change the permissions 
      of other users.
      </para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            admin
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para> 
             Indicates user is an Administrator.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>
            bz_canusewhineatothers
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para> 
             Indicates user can configure whine reports for other users.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>
             bz_canusewhines
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para> 
             Indicates user can configure whine reports for self.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>	 	
 
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
             bz_sudoers
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para> 
             Indicates user can perform actions as other users.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>	

        <varlistentry>
          <term>
             bz_sudo_protect
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para> 
             Indicates user can not be impersonated by other users.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>
             canconfirm
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para> 
             Indicates user can confirm a bug or mark it a duplicate.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>
             creategroups
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para> 
             Indicates user can create and destroy groups.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>
             editbugs
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para> 
             Indicates user can edit all bug fields.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>
             editclassifications
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para> 
             Indicates user can create, destroy, and edit classifications.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>
             editcomponents
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para> 
             Indicates user can create, destroy, and edit components.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
 
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
             editkeywords
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para> 
             Indicates user can create, destroy, and edit keywords.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>
             editusers
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para> 
             Indicates user can edit or disable users.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
	
        <varlistentry>
          <term>
             tweakparams
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para> 
             Indicates user can change Parameters.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

      </variablelist>

       <note>
        <para>
        For more information on how permissions work in Bugzilla (i.e. who can
        change what), see  <xref linkend="cust-change-permissions"/>. 
        </para>
       </note>

    </section>
  </section>
  
  
  <section id="reporting">
    <title>Reports and Charts</title>
    
    <para>As well as the standard buglist, Bugzilla has two more ways of
    viewing sets of bugs. These are the reports (which give different
    views of the current state of the database) and charts (which plot
    the changes in particular sets of bugs over time.)</para>
    
    <section id="reports">
      <title>Reports</title>
      
      <para>
        A report is a view of the current state of the bug database.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        You can run either an HTML-table-based report, or a graphical
        line/pie/bar-chart-based one. The two have different pages to
        define them, but are close cousins - once you've defined and
        viewed a report, you can switch between any of the different
        views of the data at will.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        Both report types are based on the idea of defining a set of bugs
        using the standard search interface, and then choosing some
        aspect of that set to plot on the horizontal and/or vertical axes.
        You can also get a form of 3-dimensional report by choosing to have
        multiple images or tables.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        So, for example, you could use the search form to choose "all
        bugs in the WorldControl product", and then plot their severity
        against their component to see which component had had the largest
        number of bad bugs reported against it. 
      </para>
      
      <para>
        Once you've defined your parameters and hit "Generate Report",
        you can switch between HTML, CSV, Bar, Line and Pie. (Note: Pie
        is only available if you didn't define a vertical axis, as pie
        charts don't have one.) The other controls are fairly self-explanatory;
        you can change the size of the image if you find text is overwriting
        other text, or the bars are too thin to see.
      </para>
      
    </section>
    
    <section id="charts">
      <title>Charts</title>
      
      <para>
        A chart is a view of the state of the bug database over time.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        Bugzilla currently has two charting systems - Old Charts and New 
        Charts. Old Charts have been part of Bugzilla for a long time; they
        chart each status and resolution for each product, and that's all.
        They are deprecated, and going away soon - we won't say any more 
        about them.
        New Charts are the future - they allow you to chart anything you
        can define as a search.
      </para>
      
      <note>
        <para>
          Both charting forms require the administrator to set up the
          data-gathering script. If you can't see any charts, ask them whether
          they have done so.
        </para>
      </note>
      
      <para>
        An individual line on a chart is called a data set.
        All data sets are organised into categories and subcategories. The 
        data sets that Bugzilla defines automatically use the Product name 
        as a Category and Component names as Subcategories, but there is no 
        need for you to follow that naming scheme with your own charts if 
        you don't want to.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        Data sets may be public or private. Everyone sees public data sets in
        the list, but only their creator sees private data sets. Only 
        administrators can make data sets public.
        No two data sets, even two private ones, can have the same set of 
        category, subcategory and name. So if you are creating private data 
        sets, one idea is to have the Category be your username.
      </para>
      
      <section>
        <title>Creating Charts</title>
        
        <para>
          You create a chart by selecting a number of data sets from the
          list, and pressing Add To List for each. In the List Of Data Sets
          To Plot, you can define the label that data set will have in the
          chart's legend, and also ask Bugzilla to Sum a number of data sets 
          (e.g. you could Sum data sets representing RESOLVED, VERIFIED and 
          CLOSED in a particular product to get a data set representing all 
          the resolved bugs in that product.)
        </para>

        <para>
          If you've erroneously added a data set to the list, select it
          using the checkbox and click Remove. Once you add more than one 
          data set, a "Grand Total" line
          automatically appears at the bottom of the list. If you don't want
          this, simply remove it as you would remove any other line.
        </para>
        
        <para>
          You may also choose to plot only over a certain date range, and
          to cumulate the results - that is, to plot each one using the 
          previous one as a baseline, so the top line gives a sum of all 
          the data sets. It's easier to try than to explain :-)
        </para>

        <para>
          Once a data set is in the list, one can also perform certain 
          actions on it. For example, one can edit the
          data set's parameters (name, frequency etc.) if it's one you
          created or if you are an administrator.
        </para>

        <para>
           Once you are happy, click Chart This List to see the chart.
        </para>

      </section>
      
      <section id="charts-new-series">
        <title>Creating New Data Sets</title>
        
        <para>
          You may also create new data sets of your own. To do this,
          click the "create a new data set" link on the Create Chart page.
          This takes you to a search-like interface where you can define
          the search that Bugzilla will plot. At the bottom of the page,
          you choose the category, sub-category and name of your new
          data set. 
        </para>

        <para>
          If you have sufficient permissions, you can make the data set public,
          and reduce the frequency of data collection to less than the default
          seven days.
        </para>
      </section>
      
    </section>
    
  </section>
  
  <section id="flags">
    <title>Flags</title>
    
    <para>
      A flag is a kind of status that can be set on bugs or attachments
      to indicate that the bugs/attachments are in a certain state.
      Each installation can define its own set of flags that can be set
      on bugs or attachments.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      If your installation has defined a flag, you can set or unset that flag,
      and if your administrator has enabled requesting of flags, you can submit
      a request for another user to set the flag.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      To set a flag, select either "+" or "-" from the drop-down menu next to
      the name of the flag in the "Flags" list.  The meaning of these values are
      flag-specific and thus cannot be described in this documentation,
      but by way of example, setting a flag named "review" to "+" may indicate
      that the bug/attachment has passed review, while setting it to "-"
      may indicate that the bug/attachment has failed review.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      To unset a flag, click its drop-down menu and select the blank value.
      Note that marking an attachment as obsolete automatically cancels all
      pending requests for the attachment.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      If your administrator has enabled requests for a flag, request a flag
      by selecting "?" from the drop-down menu and then entering the username
      of the user you want to set the flag in the text field next to the menu.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      A set flag appears in bug reports and on "edit attachment" pages with the
      abbreviated username of the user who set the flag prepended to the
      flag name. For example, if Jack sets a "review" flag to "+", it appears
      as Jack: review [ + ]
    </para>
  
    <para>
      A requested flag appears with the user who requested the flag prepended
      to the flag name and the user who has been requested to set the flag
      appended to the flag name within parentheses.  For example, if Jack
      asks Jill for review, it appears as Jack: review [ ? ] (Jill).
    </para>

    <para>
      You can browse through open requests made of you and by you by selecting
      'My Requests' from the footer. You can also look at open requests limited
      by other requesters, requestees, products, components, and flag names from
      this page. Note that you can use '-' for requestee to specify flags with
      'no requestee' set.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="whining">
    <title>Whining</title>

    <para>
      Whining is a feature in Bugzilla that can regularly annoy users at 
      specified times.  Using this feature, users can execute saved searches 
      at specific times (i.e. the 15th of the month at midnight) or at 
      regular intervals (i.e. every 15 minutes on Sundays).  The results of the
      searches are sent to the user, either as a single email or as one email 
      per bug, along with some descriptive text.
    </para>

    <warning>
      <para>
        Throughout this section it will be assumed that all users are members 
        of the bz_canusewhines group, membership in which is required in order 
        to use the Whining system.  You can easily make all users members of 
        the bz_canusewhines group by setting the User RegExp to ".*" (without 
        the quotes).
      </para>

      <para>
        Also worth noting is the bz_canusewhineatothers group.  Members of this
        group can create whines for any user or group in Bugzilla using a 
        extended form of the whining interface.  Features only available to 
        members of the bz_canusewhineatothers group will be noted in the 
        appropriate places.
      </para>
    </warning>

    <note>
      <para>
        For whining to work, a special Perl script must be executed at regular
        intervals.  More information on this is available in 
        <xref linkend="installation-whining"/>.
      </para>
    </note>

    <note>
      <para>
        This section does not cover the whineatnews.pl script.  See
        <xref linkend="installation-whining-cron"/> for more information on 
        The Whining Cron.
      </para>
    </note>

    <section id="whining-overview">
      <title>The Event</title>

      <para>
        The whining system defines an "Event" as one or more queries being 
        executed at regular intervals, with the results of said queries (if
        there are any) being emailed to the user.  Events are created by 
        clicking on the "Add new event" button.
      </para>

      <para>
        Once a new event is created, the first thing to set is the "Email 
        subject line".  The contents of this field will be used in the subject
        line of every email generated by this event.  In addition to setting a 
        subject, space is provided to enter some descriptive text that will be 
        included at the top of each message (to help you in understanding why 
        you received the email in the first place).
      </para>

      <para>
        The next step is to specify when the Event is to be run (the Schedule) 
        and what searches are to be performed (the Searches).
      </para>

    </section>

    <section id="whining-schedule">
      <title>Whining Schedule</title>

      <para>
         Each whining event is associated with zero or more schedules.  A 
         schedule is used to specify when the query (specified below) is to be
         run.  A new event starts out with no schedules (which means it will 
         never run, as it is not scheduled to run).  To add a schedule, press
         the "Add a new schedule" button.
      </para>

      <para>
         Each schedule includes an interval, which you use to tell Bugzilla 
         when the event should be run.  An event can be run on certain days of
         the week, certain days of the month, during weekdays (defined as 
         Monday through Friday), or every day.
      </para>

      <warning>
        <para>
          Be careful if you set your event to run on the 29th, 30th, or 31st of
          the month, as your event may not run exactly when expected.  If you 
          want your event to run on the last day of the month, select "Last day
          of the month" as the interval.
        </para>
      </warning>

      <para>
        Once you have specified the day(s) on which the event is to be run, you
        should now specify the time at which the event is to be run.  You can 
        have the event run at a certain hour on the specified day(s), or 
        every hour, half-hour, or quarter-hour on the specified day(s).
      </para>

      <para>
        If a single schedule does not execute an event as many times as you 
        would want, you can create another schedule for the same event.  For 
        example, if you want to run an event on days whose numbers are
        divisible by seven, you would need to add four schedules to the event,
        setting the schedules to run on the 7th, 14th, 21st, and 28th (one day 
        per schedule) at whatever time (or times) you choose.
      </para>

      <note>
        <para>
          If you are a member of the bz_canusewhineatothers group, then you
          will be presented with another option: "Mail to".  Using this you 
          can control who will receive the emails generated by this event.  You
          can choose to send the emails to a single user (identified by email 
          address) or a single group (identified by group name).  To send to 
          multiple users or groups, create a new schedule for each additional 
          user/group.
        </para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section id="whining-query">
      <title>Whining Searches</title>

      <para>
        Each whining event is associated with zero or more searches.  A search
        is any saved search to be run as part of the specified schedule (see
        above).  You start out without any searches associated with the event
        (which means that the event will not run, as there will never be any
        results to return).  To add a search, press the "Include search" button.
      </para>

      <para>
        The first field to examine in your newly added search is the Sort field.
        Searches are run, and results included, in the order specified by the
        Sort field.  Searches with smaller Sort values will run before searches
        with bigger Sort values.
      </para>

      <para>
        The next field to examine is the Search field.  This is where you 
        choose the actual search that is to be run.  Instead of defining search
        parameters here, you are asked to choose from the list of saved 
        searches (the same list that appears at the bottom of every Bugzilla 
        page).  You are only allowed to choose from searches that you have 
        saved yourself (the default saved search, "My Bugs", is not a valid 
        choice).  If you do not have any saved searches, you can take this 
        opportunity to create one (see <xref linkend="list"/>).
      </para>

      <note>
        <para>
          When running queries, the whining system acts as if you are the user
          executing the query.  This means that the whining system will ignore
          bugs that match your query, but that you can not access.
        </para>
      </note>

      <para>
        Once you have chosen the saved search to be executed, give the query a 
        descriptive title.  This title will appear in the email, above the 
        results of the query.  If you choose "One message per bug", the query 
        title will appear at the top of each email that contains a bug matching
        your query.
      </para>

      <para>
        Finally, decide if the results of the query should be sent in a single
        email, or if each bug should appear in its own email.
      </para>

      <warning>
        <para>
          Think carefully before checking the "One message per bug" box.  If
          you create a query that matches thousands of bugs, you will receive 
          thousands of emails!
        </para>
      </warning>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Saving Your Changes</title>

      <para>
        Once you have defined at least one schedule, and created at least one 
        query, go ahead and "Update/Commit".  This will save your Event and make
        it available for immediate execution.
      </para>

      <note>
        <para>
          If you ever feel like deleting your event, you may do so using the 
          "Remove Event" button in the upper-right corner of each Event.  You 
          can also modify an existing event, so long as you "Update/Commit" 
          after completing your modifications.
        </para>
      </note>
    </section>

  </section>

</chapter>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: sgml
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-auto-insert-required-elements:t
sgml-balanced-tag-edit:t
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-general-insert-case:lower
sgml-indent-data:t
sgml-indent-step:2
sgml-local-catalogs:nil
sgml-local-ecat-files:nil
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-namecase-general:t
sgml-omittag:t
sgml-parent-document:("Bugzilla-Guide.xml" "book" "chapter")
sgml-shorttag:t
sgml-tag-region-if-active:t
End:
-->

